<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A moste pythye and excellent epistell to anymate all trew Christians vnto the crosse of Chryste, translated out off ffre[n]che [sic] into ynglyshe by Robert Pownoll. With a preface to the reader.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112251</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847509</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847509</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12546</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00308)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12546)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 223:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A moste pythye and excellent epistell to anymate all trew Christians vnto the crosse of Chryste, translated out off ffre[n]che [sic] into ynglyshe by Robert Pownoll. With a preface to the reader.</title>
                  <author>Pownall, Robert, 1520-1571.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Lambrecht?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. M. D. L. vi. [1556]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12546:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12546:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Amoſte Py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thye and Excellent Epiſtell to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymate all trew Chriſtians vnto the Croſſe of Chryſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / Tranſlated out off ffre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che into ynglyſhe by Robert Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noll. With a pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>face to the Reader.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Marke. <hi>9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶ Every man ſhalbe ſalted with fyre: and euery ſacrefice ſhalbe ſeaſoned with ſalte.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted. An. M.D.LVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12546:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12546:2"/>
            <head>¶ Robert Pownoll vnto the Chriſtian Reader wyſſethe the grace / mercy / &amp; peace off God the ffather to be multiplyed / by the merytes off Ieſus Chriſte / trought the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication off the holy Goſte. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarye the croſſe yo vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>AS there ys no thynge more requyſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, neceſſarye, &amp; profytable for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrmation off a Chryſtian lyffe (O here Reader) then the Croſſe &amp; perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: So ys there no thynge, in theſe dayes, more fered, ſhouned &amp; avoyded, &amp; that off thoſſe that wold becounted conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans &amp; erneſt goſpellers, ſhuche ys theyre imbecillite, weaknes &amp; folymnes: myche lyke vnto lytell chyldren, who cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye do deſyre the ſwete meatte that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the anoye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; fle from the bytter thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge that may do them good. For truly the Croſſe &amp; perſecution (yf we wyl put chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyſhnes apart,<note place="margin">The vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of the Croſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by dyvers ſimi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litudes.</note> &amp; wyſely waye the worth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes therof) It ys that ſoueraigne tryed treacle, that quencheth the deadly degeſted poyſon, off ſelfe love, wordly pleaſure, fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly felycyte &amp; carnale ſecuryte. It ys the only worthy worme poyſon, off ambyſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:12546:3"/>covytouſnes, fornycation, dronckenes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torcion, vnclenes, lyſencious lybertye, glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tony, wrathe, ſtryffe, ſedycion, ſectes, maly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, &amp; ſhuche other lyke wreched wayward wormes. It ys the o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly profitable plowght whoſſe property ys, not only to Rote vp all briers, brambelles, Thyſielles, Thornes &amp; wedes, out of the earthly hart &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence off mortal men, but alſo to prepare &amp; yeld the ſame apte to reſſayve the ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſeade of chryſtes ſowynge in his goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell preachynge. It ys the hard hamuier that beateth off the Rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Buſt from the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Anker off a chryſtian fayght, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parynge the ſame to all good excercyſes, whych other wayes wold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume awaye.</p>
            <p>It ys that fyrye flamynge ffor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace that puryfyethe the good golde, in burnynge vp all the drowſye droſſe off ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s dyſſayva<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble luſies. It ys the proynige knyffe wher with the rotten, drye &amp; droppynge bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches off the the vyne of a chriſtian lyffe ys cute awaye, whych by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyne wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce myght vterly waſt, &amp; yelde the ſame vnfrutfull. It ys that ſavorye ſalte that conſumethe awaye the corruption off chryſtians, in ſeaſonynge theyre lyffes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o all profytable vſes. It ys that trew towche ſtone, that tryethe gold from copper, the trew
<pb facs="tcp:12546:3"/>from the counterfeit, &amp; the fyne, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that whych ys baſſe. ffynaly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude. The croſſe &amp; perſecution ys that floryſhynge flayſe &amp; fan, that pourgethe &amp; delyverethe the good corne off a chryſtian lyffe, from all chaffe off corruption, wherewyth befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re it was covered, O profytable Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.<note place="margin">The Croſſe can not be ſpared.</note> O neceſſarye Towel, O excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerſyce that cannot be ſpared in a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyffe. For yff a poyſoned perſon, may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t treacle? Yff Iron may wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>met? The earthe the ploughte? The gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the fornace? And the corne the ffayle &amp; fan? Then may a Chriſtyan ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> want the croſſe &amp; tribulation? or els not. Wherfor theſſe thynges wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered, with what alacryete off mynde?<note place="margin">Iere. 16. Math. 20 Marc. 10.</note> With what deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous affection? And with what erneſt zeale? Ought we to imbrace this incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable iewell, this ſoueraigne medecyn, this comfortable cuppe off the Croſſe and tribulation?<note place="margin">The comode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes that the croſſe brine<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth vnto chriſtians.</note> wherin with out all doute the lorde hath prepared a draught for his ſaynctes to dryncke (all thought ſome what tarte &amp; bytter vnto the fleſche) yet ys it moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable &amp; pleaſant vnto the ſoul. For it ys vnto hyr a moſt profytable purgation off power able to purge awaye the pampred pleaſures off the fylthy fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:12546:4"/>redy to infect hyr. Yea it ys the only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fortable conſeruatyue that dothe conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue hyr from all infectyve eayres, deadly poyſone, &amp; contagious ſycknes off ſynne, the only dyſtruction off man kynde.<note place="margin">Eccle. 38. Math. 9. Marc. 2. Luc. 5.</note> For loke how neceſſarye the phiſition ys vnto the Sycke, the byttynge corſyve vnto the feſtured ſore, the ſharpe lancere vnto the molyfyed matter. Even ſo with out al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paryſon the croſſe &amp; tribulation, ys more neceſſary vnto a chriſtian. Forby it the ſyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knes off ſynne ys removed, the feſtred ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of fleſly luſt ys cured, &amp; the ſuperfleous humors of eartly pleaſure are cut a waye. Wherefor yff we were not all to gyther voyde off vnderſtanding, &amp; more inſenſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then the brut beſies, yea yff we were not more carnall then ſpyrytuall, more worldly, then hevenly, we wolde not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake ſo wholſom a ſalve, as ſervethe ffor all dyſeaſes. For by it the worlde ys crucy fyed vnto vs,<note place="margin">Galat. 6. Roma. 8. Roma. 5.</note> &amp; we vnto the worlde, by it we are made lyke vnto the image off the ſonne off God. By it oure fayght ys increſed, oure pacience excerſyſed, &amp; oure hope augmented. By it we are knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bothe within &amp; with out, to oure ſelves &amp; to other men. By it we are aſſerteyned of oure ſaluation,<note place="margin">Roma. 8.</note> for yff we ſuffer with
<pb facs="tcp:12546:4"/>chryſt, we ſhall raigne with hym. Fynaly to conclude, by it we moſt enter into the kyngdom off God, for it ys written, by many tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s we moſt enter into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> kingdom off heaven.<note place="margin">Act. 14. Math. 7.</note> It ys that only na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſtrayte waye that leadeth vnto lyffe. Wherfor my ffrynde, yff thow deſyre to lyve &amp; not to dye. Yff thow deſyre to be ſaved &amp; not to be condemned.<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> Yff thow deſyre to have chryſte to confeſſe the, &amp; not to denye the, before his father &amp; his ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Yff thow deſyre to folowe the ſonne off God into his kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed thens. Gyue eare then vnto this ſentence for therin he teaceth the, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waye vnto the ſame, ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge, he that wil follew me let hym take vp his croſſe &amp; fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe me.<note place="margin">Math. 16. Marc. 8. Luc. 9.14 hovv vve ſhould fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovve chriſt</note> Wherby it is appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we can not ffollowe chryſte, but by berynge a Croſſe, not the croſſe off the tower off gold &amp; ſylver, nor yet the papiſticale croſſe of Idolatrye which ſo many now a dayes do followe. But the croſſe off perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aflyction &amp; mortyfycation,<note place="margin">Iohan. 14</note> For yff Chriſt be oure waye (as he ſayeth he ys) vnto his father &amp; that beſyde hym there ys no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other but bye wayes tendynge to perdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">The onlj na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rovve vvaije <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ys it off neceſſite, yff we wyll come vnto eternall glorye, that we do travayll that
<pb facs="tcp:12546:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>waye that he hath gone before vs, in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge his fotſteppes.<note place="margin">The kijngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heaven, die the croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and tribu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation.</note> For yff he oure hedd be entred into the kyngdome off God by non other waye, but by croſſe &amp; tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, can we his members enter any other ☜ waye? Who euer ſawe the hedd go into a place one waye, &amp; the members a nother waye vnleſe they were devyded &amp; cut of?<note place="margin">Math. 27 Marc. 15. Luc. 23. Act. 1.2.</note> Ieſꝰ Chryſt entred into the kyngdome of his father, by Ignomyne, Reproffe, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, ſklander, Revylynge perſecution. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction &amp; Croſſe, and can we his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, (yff we do contynew the members of his body) enter any other waye? no truly. For then were there awaye beſydes the ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tel narowe waye, which he hath ſhowed vs. Then were theſſe his ſaymges tryed vntrew. Whereas he ſayd vnto his dyſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples &amp; in them to vs. Yff they haue perſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuted me,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15 Math. 10. Ioh. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Reg. 22 Pſal. 80. Pſal. 30. Pſal. 44.</note> they ſhal alſo perſecute you. Yff they haue called the maſter off the howſſe Belzebub, how myche more ſhall they cal the howſhold ſeruantes ſo. Dure porſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this lyffe ys to wepe &amp; morne. To taſt the bread off aduerſyte &amp; the water of tro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. To be as ſheppe appoynted to the ſlaughter. Theſſe are the daynty dyſhes that God hath prepared for his chyldrin to ffede on in this worlde, To thende that
<pb facs="tcp:12546:5"/>in the worlde to come,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16. Apoc. 7.22.</note> they may laughe &amp; reioyſe, hauynge al teares wyped a waye ffrom theyr eyes, &amp; ffede with the celeſtial ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na &amp; water off lyffe, in triumphynge ouer theyre enymes. For in this worlde (as ſayeth S Paul) we are iudged &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flycted,<note place="margin">1. cor. 11. All thoughs vve are in this vvorld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned. jet in the vvorlde to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vve ſhal be glorified Luc. 16.</note> be cauſe we ſhoulde not be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the worlde. Whereby it ys ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that to ſeke to enioye the quyetnes off this worlde ys no thynge els but to ſeke to be condemned with the vngodly, whoſſe por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>n ys here to laughe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyſſe, &amp; here after to wepe &amp; wayle. As it apperethe by the hyſtorye of Dyves, to whom Abraham ſayd, Sonne, remember that thow in thy lyffe tyme reſſayveſt thy pleaſure, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary wyſſe Lazarus reſſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved payne, but now ys he comforted, and thow art ponyſhed. So that to lyve here in pleaſure &amp; ſecurite with delectaſion in the ſame, ys no thynge els but to reſſayve payne with out comfort in the lyffe to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Wherefor dere reader fle fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ioye &amp; pleaſure, as from a moſt peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent poyſon, for all thought the preſent taſt therof be pleaſant, yet ys the ende ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>off eternall damnation to as many as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte there in.<note place="margin">Be vvare of the vaine</note> Stoppe thyn eares at the ſwet ſinginge of theſſe byſſevable Serenes
<pb facs="tcp:12546:6"/>Leſt thow beynge lulled a ſlepe ther by,<note place="margin">Pſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>on of vvordlj me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ijxe thij hart on ert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lij thijng. Dani. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Apoc 18. Math. 7.</note> thow peryſhe euerlaſtyngly. Be ware, be not dyſſayved with the melodious muſyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke &amp; pleaſat armonye of this worlde which ſerveth for no thyng els but to allure the from God, vnto the devell, from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe pathe off ſalvation vnto the brode waye off damnation, From the trew honorynge off God, vnto all kynde off ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latrye, and from the ryght religion, vnto ſervyle ſuperſticion. Lerne to be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (as ſayeth the prouerbe) by an other mans harme. Let the wofull traged ye off oure fyrſt father Adam ſerve to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe vs: for the old ſerpent the devell ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the not forgotten his accuſtomed tryckes to temple vs as hs tempted Adam, with the apple off wordly pleaſure, ſecuryte &amp; caſe,<note place="margin">Gene. 3.</note> the which all thought it haue a plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſant taſte in the mouthe, yt ys it very byt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter &amp; damnable to the ſoul. And therfor oure hedd and maſter Ieſus Chriſte the ſecou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Adam &amp; fountayne off al wyſdom wold gyve no place vnto ſhuche ſuttell aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſautes off the devell,<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> but ſayed vnto hym, heus fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me Sathan thow adverſarye &amp; tempter. O that we wolde lerne of this oure ſcholmaſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">The vvorl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de js no le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braced, then</note> to byde the worlde far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, when as we cannot enioye the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:12546:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>with a pure conſyente in the fere off God,<note place="margin">vvhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lles vve mai po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſe chriſt vvith the ſame.</note> and obediently to bende oure backes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the borthen off chriſtes croſſe in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion off his worde. And to thende thow mayſt the better he incorraged paciently to bere the croſſe that it ſhall pleaſe chriſt to charge the with all. I haue (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to myn accuſtomed rudnes) tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this excellent epyſtell out off the fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che into oure Inglyſhe tounge.<note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll.</note> The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors name, I knowe not. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende it, I nede not, for good wyne nedethe no banner. Fyrſt reade, &amp; then Iudge. Off this I am ſure, that in hyt thow ſhalt ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne (yff truthe may teache the) to throwe done thy ſelfe vnder the myghty hande of god i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyllyngly ſubmyttynge thy ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his wyll, which ys the fyrſt prynciple off trew chryſtianyte. Thow ſhalt alſo ſerue, what ys the wyll off God towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des his churche, &amp; how he hathe intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hyr fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme to tyme. Fynally, bycau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe I wyll a voyde prolyxite, (beſyde plen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty off other pyththy matters) in hyt thow haſt abreffe Somacye and gatherynge to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyther of al the comfortable places of the ſcryptures, that may ſarve to induce vs paciently to ſuffer afflyction for the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the truthe, in what ſorte it ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:12546:7"/>pleaſe the eternall God, oure moſt dere &amp; lovynge father to laye theſame vpon vs. Yff thow art any thynge therby comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; ſtrenthened (as I am ſure thow ſhalt be, yff thow reade theſame with a ſyngle &amp; pure mynde, &amp; not by cauſe thow wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be counted a reader off many new bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, but bycauſe thow deſyreſt to be edy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by them) gyve the glorye vnto God,<note place="margin">Red not for novelties ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e but to be edified.</note> who hath wrought ſhuche worthy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes in his creatures. And I dout not but here in thow ſhalte fynde thyne ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pectacion, to thy ſynguler conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. The name off the Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be prayſed who hath made bothe heaven and earthe, and in dyſpyte off his enymes hath pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared a reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce for his churche.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:12546:7"/>
            <head>¶ THE EPISTEL.</head>
            <p>AMONGEST OTHER NE<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſary thynges that Ieſus Chriſte the alone Savioure off the worlde, &amp; the only trew &amp; perfyte maſter of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall churche, hath comanded vs to aſke of God his father &amp; oures throught hym, we fynde wryten that he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſilly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded vs all wayes to ſaye (Dure father thy wyll be done) And as this prayer ought not to proſede from the mouthe only,<note place="margin">Math. 6. Luc. 11.</note> ſo ys it neceſſarye that the mouthe do all wayes ſpeke off the abon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the harte,<note place="margin">Math. 12.</note> that ys to ſaye not fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nedly, but perfectlye &amp; intyrlye, all war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es deſyrynge the accomplyſhynge off the good wyll off God oure celeſtiall father. Beynge all wayes redy to gyve thankes &amp; to reioyſe when we ſhall ſe the wyll off God accomplyſhed, ether vpon vs, or vpon any other, ether in proſperyte or ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſyte, the which all wayes the fleſſhe dothe abhorre. For that prayer that ys voyde off this vnfayned deſyre, beynge preſented vnto God, ys not only a mere Ipocreſye, but alſo a playne mockynge off hys maieſtye.<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> But on the other ſyde this devyne &amp; chryſtean deſyre dothe yelde
<pb facs="tcp:12546:8"/>oure prayer all to gyther, impoluted and perfy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e before the lorde. For all thynges duly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered, there are dyvers vrge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, that ought all wayes to move vs, to beſyre the performance off the wyll off God oure moſt benynge father. Do we not knowe perfytly, that the lorde hath made all thynges accordynge to his owne pleaſure,<note place="margin">Gene. 1. Eccle. 39.</note> for hym ſelfe? So not we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that all thynges were created by the wyll off the lorde God only? Yff it be ſo then that all thynges were made by the only wyll off God? What othere thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ought we to deſyre, but only that this his wyll be accomplyſhed &amp; performed? The which can be non other, but good &amp; Iuſte. Yff we were wyſſe I nought to vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand this perfyt leſſon, that the lorde God dothe preche vnto vs, by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; mynyſtration off all his other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wolde we moſt wyllyngly &amp; gladly deſyre to ſe the accomplyſhment off this his wyl vpon vs, in al thynges that it pleaſeth hym to do with vs. We are not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t off this, that God hath not created his creatures, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d they ſhould be ſubiect to vanyte (that ys to ſave) to mutacion &amp; corruption, &amp; to the abus off
<pb facs="tcp:12546:8"/>the vnbelevers. For it ys moſt certayne that all the creatures on theyre behalfe do rather deſyre not to be ſubiecte vnto ifyde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> then to be ſubiect, for naturally they do deſyre all to gyther, to enioye theyre perfyte ſtate wherin they were created. But, when as (after theyre faſſion) they do conſyder, that God hath ſo ordayned it, that for a tyme they ſhould ſerue the wycked &amp; vnbelevers, they beare with out repynyng this myſerable ſeruytude, for the honour off hym that hath ſubiected the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there vnto, in hopynge moſt certayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ons they ſhalbe delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that bondage, all thought they do neyther for ſe the tyme, when, not the meanes, how. Now then I wold demande off you, bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therin moſt derely beloved, not in Adam,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15</note> in whom ys no thynge but perdyction, but in Ieſus Chryſte in whom only ys oi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re perfyte ſalvation,<note place="margin">Act. 4. Hebre. 2</note> ſtandythe it with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny equyte or reaſon that all other creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res obaynge the good wyll of God the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, that we ſhould gaynſaye &amp; obſtynatly with ſtande theſame, when as he dothe with vs accordynge as it beſt pleaſeth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Truly God ys more vnto vs, then he ys vnto all other hys creatures, for he ys oure father, and we are more vnto hym,
<pb facs="tcp:12546:9"/>then all his other creatures, for we are his chylderne, and we are his heyres, we ought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to love hym more then al other his creatures, we ought to haue in hym a more lyvely hope &amp; confydence with grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter effycace, then all other creatures, So that by good conſequence we ought more wyllyngly to ſubmyte oure ſelfes vnto his good pleaſure then all other his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in ſaynge all wayes, Thy wyll be done. But what ſuppoſe we to be the wyll &amp; ordynance off God? S. Paul do the notably teache vs theſame, where as he ſaythe.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Thoſſe whom God hath know en from the begynynge, he hath predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to thende they ſhould be made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrmable to the image off his Soune. This breffe ſentence off the holy apoſtell well vnderſtanded, dothe playnly expreſe vnto vs, what the wyll and ordyna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce off God ys to vs warde. The which dothe this myche ſygnyfye vnto vs, that God hath immutablye ordayned that all thoſſe whom he hath choſen before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtytuti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on off the worlde ſhould be made lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ieſus Chryſte his ſonne. I appeſe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vnto all your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyences (D ye chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) and do demaunde off you, ys there
<pb facs="tcp:12546:9"/>any ryches, ys there any honour, ys the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re any glorye, ys there any tryvn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>phe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto thys? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amly to be made co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble vnto the ſonne off God? No truly, iudge ye yourſeldes, wherfor prayſed be the eternall name off the Lord our God, who trought his infynyte bounty, with out any off oure deſertes,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.</note> hathe choſſen vs, &amp; made vs worthy off this incompara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble felycyte and honour. But this avay lethe no thynge vnto hym that vnderſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not theſame. Wherfor it behoveth vs dylygently to waye &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder what the ſcrypture mene the whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it affyrmethe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that it ys the wyl of the lorde God oure father, that we ſhould be lyke vnto the image off his ſonne, who ys the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and only ſonne off God, even Ieſus Chriſte in whom we do beleve, &amp; of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we do beare the holy name off chriſtians. And where ys he now? he ys lyvynge &amp; raynynge with God his father in immor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>talyte moſt happye,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> whoſſe wyll ys that we ſhoulde be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmable in glorye to the image off his ſonne, as wytneſethe. S. Paul, in the place before reſyted. To the which alſo agreethe. S. Iohn,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.</note> when as he ſayethe, whe knowe that when he
<pb facs="tcp:12546:10"/>ſhall appere, we ſhalde lyke vnto hym.</p>
            <p>Wherby it ys manyfeſe, that we ſhal vs lyve &amp; raigne with hym, the which thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge moſt certaynly ſhall come to pas, for he hym ſelfe dothe make vs there off a moſt perfyt promys,<note place="margin">Luc. 12.</note> in theſſe wordes, ffere not lytiell flocke, for it hath pleaſed your father to gyve you a kyngdom. Shall not we then haue it? Truly, we ſhall haue it. for as ſaythe Mardocheur,<note place="margin">Eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 13.</note> The lorde ys an allmyghty kynge, &amp; all thynges are in his power, &amp; there ys no man that can re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyſt his wyll, wherfor yff he haue purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to delyuer Iſraell, who ſhal lett it? ſhall we not then be all ſaved? yes, ſhall we not all lyve and raigne with Chryſt? who wyll comunycate vnto vs his glorye &amp; immortalyte as the fyrſt borne a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt many brytherne, &amp; that oure God hath wylled it ſo to be, &amp; hath ordayned it to be ſo? There ys no doute theroff. And truly I ſuppoſe, there ys none off vs all that wold not gladly be pertaker with Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt in this reſpecte. For we all dely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re to be ſaved, we all deſyre to be happye, we all deſyre to lyve &amp; raigne with Ieſus Chriſte: but how the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Yf we do no thynge els but raigne with hi, we ſhall not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in
<pb facs="tcp:12546:10"/>all reſpectes be lyke vnto the Sonne off God.</p>
            <p>For the Sonne off God doth not only raigne but before he aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into his glorye, he was a ſeruant, he was a ſubiect, he ſuffred.<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> he was crucyfy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed &amp; all for vs. Wherfor yff we deſyre to be made perfytly lyke vnto Ieſus Chriſte, then moſt we beare his croſſe, ffor yff we ſhould raigne with hym, with out beynge trucyfyed with hym, we ſhould be (as it were) but in one reſpect lyke vnto hym, but God hath wylled that we ſhoulde be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmable &amp; lyke vnto hym, not in halfe or in parte, but in all thynges.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.</note> Then ys it off neceſſyte that we ſuffer with hym, and that ons ended, we are certayne that we ſhalbe gloryfyed with hym. So that there ys non other waye to enter into the glory off God, but only that waye wherby Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chryſte his ſonne ys entred. And this waye ys the croſſe. For yff we do dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rectly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder how Chriſt entred into the glory off his father, wayinge therin the immutable ordynance off God &amp; the infal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyble veryte off his holy worde we may ſaye, &amp; ſaye truly, that it was off neceſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te that Ieſus Chriſt dyd enter into his glorye by croſſe, afflyction and deathe, for other wyſſe the ordyna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God had byn
<pb facs="tcp:12546:11"/>all to gyther infrynged and broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the holy ſcryptures fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>de fals. For God by his eternall counſayll had before determy: ned that he ſhould be put to deathe,<note place="margin">Math. 16.20.28.</note> &amp; the ſcryptures lykewyſſe dyd before teſtyfye the ſame, the which thynge to be trew, namly that God hath before ordayned that Ieſus his ſonne ſhould ſuffer deathe, he hym ſelfe doth wyines vnto vs the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, when as in. S. Luc he ſayethe. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſonne off man dothe go, accordyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge as it is determyned off hym, &amp;c. Lyk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſſe. S. Peter ſpeking vnto the Iewes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hym, dothe manyfeſtly declare the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, by theſſe wordes, ye haue (ſayth he) kylled hym,<note place="margin">Act. 3.</note> in affiyetynge hym by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des off vnryghtous men, after he was de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuered by the determyuate counſayll and fore knowlege off God. Alſo the pryma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyve churche in a prayer written in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, wherin they make reherſall off thoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thynges that the ſonne off God dyd ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer, they do euydently declare vnto vs, that all that euer happyned vnto hym, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to pas,<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> by the only wyll, pleaſure &amp; ordy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance off: God his father, for they ſaye, truly Herode &amp; Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cius Pilate with the gentylles &amp; the people off Iſraell haue ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thered
<pb facs="tcp:12546:11"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelves to gyther in this cyte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thy holy c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ylde Ieſus, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thow haſt anoyncted. But where to came they to gythere? For to do what ſo euer thy hande &amp; thy counſyll had before determy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be done. Ys it not now apparant before your eyes, how that the holy goſt who ſpekynge by the holy ſcryptures doth attrybute all the ſuffrynge off Ieſus Chryſt vnto the determynate counſayll &amp; immutable ordyna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce off God his father? Lykwiſſe Ieſus Chryſt hym ſelfe beynge entred into the depe &amp; perfyte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on off this immutable determynation, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed vnto his dyſſyples,<note place="margin">Luc. 9.</note> hyt be hovethe the ſonne off ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuffer many thynges &amp; to be reproved off the elders &amp; off the hyghe preſtes, &amp; Scrybes, &amp; be ſlayne, &amp; the thyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de daye to ryſſe agayne. But wherfor, (O lorde Ieſus) behoved it ſo to be? It behoved it ſo to be, for as myche as God had ſo ordayned it, who ſayeth by the mou the off the prophet Eſaias, truly it ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, as I have determyned,<note place="margin">Eſai. 62.50.</note> and ſhall com to pas as I haue purpoſed it in my myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. The lorde off hoſtes hath decreed it, &amp; who ys he that can canſell that decre? My cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayll ſhall take place &amp; a byde, ſayeth
<pb facs="tcp:12546:12"/>the lorde God, &amp; all my wyll ſhalbe accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plyſhed. For as myche then as God hath wylled that Ieſus his ſonne ſhould be put to deathe, hauynge ſo ordayned it by his eternall counſayll. Was it not then off neceſſyte that it ſhould ſo come to pas? Hyt could be non other wyſſe. Wherfor to prowe that the holy ſcriptures dyd teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye before that Ieſus the only ſavyoure of the worlde, ſhould be put to deathe, ſhuche as haue but a lytell pervſed the word off God, are not ignorant off the ſame. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the not he hym ſelfe ſaye?<note place="margin">Math. 26 Marc. 14 Luc. 22. Iohan. 5. Eſa. 30.52.</note> The ſonne off man goethe as it ys wrytten off hym? Yff we would take the payne (as we ought to do &amp; as we are comaunded) to ſerche dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly the ſcryptures, we ſhould fynde that not only they haue propheſyed his deathe, but alſo they haue propheſied (yea &amp; that partycularely) all other thynges that he hathe ſuffred for vs. So that it behoved hym off neceſſyte, to ſuffer all that he hath ſuffred. And therfor he ſayd vnto his dyſſyples, it behoued me to accomply ſhe all that was wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me in the lawe off Moyſes,<note place="margin">Luc. 24.</note> in the prophetes, &amp; in the pſalmes. And agayne he ſayd vnto them, thus it ys it written, &amp; thus it beho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bed Chryſte to ſuffer. And a lytell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:12546:12"/>that, he ſayd vnto tow off his diſſyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les which were goynge vnto Emaus,<note place="margin">Luc. 14.</note> O folles &amp; ſlowe off hert to beleve all that the prophetes haue ſpoken, was it not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quyſyte that Chryſt ſhoulde ſuffer theſſe thynghe, &amp; ſo enter into his glorye? He ſayethe that it ys requyſyte &amp; neceſſarye, that by the croſſe he ſhould enter into his glorye. But wherfor was it ſo requyſyte &amp; neceſſarye? It was neceſſarye, fyrſt, for as myche as God had ſo ordayned it, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, by cauſe it was ſo wrytten &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſyed off hym. But for all that it beho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved hi neceſſarily to ſuffer beathe, yet not with ſtandynge he dyd not ſuffer the ſame by coaction and conſtraynt or agaynſt his wyl, but he dyd wyllyngly obaye the moſt mercyfull ordyna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce off God his father, &amp; with a fre conſent off hart dyd acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſhe the holy ſcryptures, to thende he myght render vnto God his father the glory off all truthe. And to prove that Ieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt hath bothe wyllyngly &amp; obedyently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted hym ſelfe vnto the wyll off God his father, the holy ſcrypture teſtyfyeth euery where, &amp; it is evydently apparant vnto all thoſſe, to whom God hathe give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace to knowe parfytly what ys Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:12546:13"/>Chryſt, for he ys properly that trew Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyd, who hathe fully accomplyſhed the wyll off his lorde God, (that ys to ſaye) he hath done all that he wolde haue hym do. But no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can accomplyſh the wyll off God, yff he do it not wyllyngly &amp; with all his harte, ffor the lawe ys ſpyrytuall as ſayeth. O. Paul,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> that ys to ſaye it requy rethe the ſpirete &amp; the fre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent off the har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, &amp; can none other wyſſe be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſhed, but by doynge wyllynglye the thynge that it commandethe: yea a man muſt haue his wholl delyte in the law off God (as ſayeth the prophet) other wyſſe it ys no thynge els but mere Ipoeryſye &amp; a playne mockynge off God.<note place="margin">pſal. 1.</note> But Ieſus Chriſre which ys the veryte it ſelfe, coulde bens hypocryte. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd he willynglye accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ply ſhe the wyll off God his father in all thyng, &amp; namlye in ſuffrynge. It ys evy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent then, that he hathe willyngly, gladly, and with all his harte ſuffred, that he dyd ſuffer, yea &amp; yff we will narowly examy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the matter, we ſhall fynde that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deſyred any thynge ſo erneſtly as to ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>comply ſhe the good will &amp; pleaſure of his father, or rather to ſpeke more truly we ſhal fynde that he neuer deſyred any other
<pb facs="tcp:12546:13"/>thynge. The which thyng to be trew he hym ſelfe dothe evydently wytneſſe the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame vnto vs,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note> in theſſe wordes. My me ate ys to do the wyll off hym that ſent me, &amp; to fynyſhe hys worke. That ys to ſaye. I deſyre non other thynge, but to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complyſhe the wyll off my father, and to brynge to effecte the worke that he hath gyven me in charge. But what worke was it that his father had gyven hym in charge? Truly amongeſt other thynges he gave hym in charge to ſuffer deathe for his electe. Wherby it ys appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that he deſyred no thynge ſo myche as to dye ffor the ſalvation off the chylderen off God, the which thynge he hym ſelfe declarethe evidently by the pen off. O. Luke, in theſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe wordes.<note place="margin">Luc. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> I muſt be baptyſed with a baptiſme, &amp; how am I payned tyll it be ended? Which ſignyfyeth as myche as yff he had ſayd, God my father hath orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that I ſhall dye, wherfor it be hoveth off neceſſite that I do dye, the which thyn ge truly I do muſt deſyre with all my har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, ſeynge it ſo pleaſethe the benygnite of my father, &amp; I ſhall neuer be in quyete &amp; at reſt tyll it be accomplyſhed &amp; ended.</p>
            <p>Theſſe wordes well conſydered, do they
<pb facs="tcp:12546:14"/>ſignifye, that Ieſus oure ſavioure dyd dye vnwillyngly or with repenynge? No teu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But contrarywyffe they do ſignifye that willingly &amp; with a good will, he dyd obaye the determinate ordinance off God his father, even vnto the deathe. The which thynge he hath not expreſſed vnto vs by wordes only, that he wolde dye for vs in obaynge the will off his father: but alſo he hath declared theſame by other ieſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures &amp; ſignes. As when he comonynge with his apoſtelles the fyrſt tyme, off the order off his deathe, ſaynge, that he muſt go vp to Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Math. 16</note> &amp; there ſuffer dyvers thynges of the elders, hyghe preiſtes &amp; ſcry bes, &amp; muſt be kylled, &amp; rayſed vp agayne the thyrde daye. Then Peter toke hym aſyde and begaue to rebuke hym, ſaynge, maſter, favour thy ſelfe, this ſhall not hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen vnto the. As who wolde ſaye, maſter for godes ſake beware off them, &amp; take he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de leſt they put the do deathe. O curſed wyſdome off the fleſhe, &amp; humayne vnder ſtandyng? But let vs heare what the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de dyd anſwer him. Dyd he ſaye vnto him? Peter my frynde, the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayll that thow gyveſt me cannot proſede but from good will and harty love, yea it proſede
<pb facs="tcp:12546:14"/>the from that great &amp; perſyte amyte and frendſhype which thow beareſt vnto me, wherfor I will beleve the, and folowe it, yea I will beware off this generation, and will not come at Ieruſalem. Ieſus Chriſt dyd not make him this anſwere. But what then? Be ſayd vnto him, as it were in a great coller. Go after me Sathan, thow art offencyve vnto me, for thow ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boreſt not the thynges that are off God, but thoſſe that are off men. Bere we may ſe how that he callethe his owne diſſyple. Sathan, &amp; adverſarye to God, by cauſe he went about to diſſuade him that he ſhoul be not dye, as God his father had orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, &amp; the prophetes teſtifyed. Ys not this then a moſt certayn ſygne and token that he we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t willyngly vnto the deathe for vs? The which thynge the prophetes dyd propheſye that had wrytten off him. And a mongeſt other, yff ye lyſte to heare a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne &amp; trew teſtimonye, harken what the kynge off Ieruſalem the prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid ſayethe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.</note> ſpekynge in the perſon off Chriſte. Sacrifice &amp; oblations thow wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not haue (ſayeth he) but myn eares haſt thow opened (that ys to ſaye) thow haſt made me obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the. Burnt of
<pb facs="tcp:12546:15"/>feinges &amp; ſacrifice for ſynne thow haſt not required, then ſayd I, Lo, I come, in the vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lume off the boke (that ys to ſaye in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we off God) it ys wrytten off me, that I ſhoulde fulfyll thy will, O my god, I am content to do it, &amp; thy lawe ys with in my harte. This ys the teſtimone that Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid beareth off the Meſſias. The lyke thinge viterethe the Prophet Eſaie, the trew Bomere off the prophetes.<note place="margin">Eſai. 50.</note> The lorde God (ſayeth he) hath opyned myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eare, (that ys to ſaye he hath gyuen me the gyfte off trew, perfite &amp; voluntari ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>edience), &amp; I cannot ſaye naye, nor with draw my ſelfe (that ys to ſaye I haue not ſtriven againſt his will) but I haue offred my back vnto the ſmiters, &amp; my chekes vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the nyppers, I turne not my face from ſhame and ſpittynge and from them that wolde ſcratche me by theſame, for the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de God ys my helper, and therfor ſhall I not be confounded, I haue hardened my face lyke a flynt ſtone, for I am ſure, I ſhall not come to confuſion. Behold my dere brytherin &amp; fayghtfull fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, be holde, in how fewe wordes, the perfi te &amp; voluntarye obedience off Ieſus Chriſt ys dyrectly declared as wyll by David as by
<pb facs="tcp:12546:15"/>Eſaias. But it ys no thinge to conſider &amp; knowe that Ieſus the annoynted off the lorde hath volunfarely and willingly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fred all thynges, eya even deathe it ſelfe, yff we do not alſo narowly conſider, one thinge,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> wheroff S. Peter dothe admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe vs. And what ye that? Ieſus Chriſt (ſayeth he) hath ſuffred for vs, levinge vs an example to folowe his fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſteppes. That ys to ſaye, that ye do as he hath do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. It was requiſite &amp; neceſſarye that Ieſ Chriſt ſhould ſuffer. But wherfor was it requiſite? By cauſe God had ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> orday<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned it. And the holy ſcriptures ſo teſtified it. Wherfor to obaye the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, and to accompliſhe the holy ſcriptures he dyd ſuffer, &amp; that gladly &amp; willingly. But what then? The ordinance off God dothe it tende no farther but only ouer the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon off Ieſus Chriſit?<note place="margin">Ephe. 1. 1. Cor. 11.</note> Truly the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God dothe extende ouer al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynges vniuerſally, but chefly ow<hi rend="sup">c</hi> vs that are the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of Ieſus Chriſte. And as the ſcriptures do ſpeke principally off Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> who ys the accompliſhment &amp; ende off the lawe, even ſo alſo do they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ſpeke of vs,<note place="margin">Collo. 1. Ephe. 2.</note> who by grace are made one with him. But what ys the
<pb facs="tcp:12546:16"/>ordynance off God ouer ve? He hath or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dained that we do fyrſt ſuffer with Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te before we ſhalbe glorified with him.</p>
            <p>For he hath predeſtinate vs to be lyke vnto his ſonne, in that by the croſſe he ys en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into his glorie, &amp; not otherwyſſe.</p>
            <p>And therfor. ſ. Paul hauynge reſpect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this immutable ordinance, writtinge vnto the Romaines, ſaiethe.<note place="margin">Roma. 8.</note> The ſpiret of god rendrethe teſtimonie vnto oure ſpiret that we are the childerin off God, yff we be childerin then are we alſo heires, the heires I meane of God &amp; coheriters with Chriſt, yff ſo be (ſayth. ſ. Paul) that we do ſuffer with him, that we may be alſo glorified to gyther with him. Conſider I pray you herin the minde off. S. Paul. who plainly affirmethe that we haue no part with Chriſt in glorie, vnles we do participate with him in miſerie. And a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaine witting to Timothe,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.</note> It is a trew ſainge (ſaith. S. Paul) yff we dye with him, we ſhall alſo lyve with him, yff we be paciente, we ſhal alſo raigne with him yff we denye him, he ſhall alſo denye vs.</p>
            <p>This ys the ordinance &amp; determination of God ouer vs. But now let is ſe what the ſcripture ſpeketh off vs, that ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb facs="tcp:12546:16"/>(I ſay) which in all thinges ys confir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mable to the ordinance of God, the which alſo (to ſpeke more properly) ys no thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge els but an expreſſive regeſter off the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine &amp; all mighty ordinance off the lorde.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> But what ſaieth this ſcripture co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge vs? It ſaieth.<note place="margin">Marc. 9.</note> Euery man ſhalbe ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with fyre, &amp; euery ſacrifice ſhalbe ſeſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned with ſalt. What ys that to ſaye? I take it, as yff the lord had ſayed. God ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed in the lawe off Moiſes, all thy ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhalbe ſeſoned with ſalt,<note place="margin">Leuiti. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nether ſhalt thow take a waye the ſalt off the covenant off thy God fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off the ſacrefice, but thow ſhalt offer ſalt on all thyne oblations.</p>
            <p>Wherby it ys apparant that it was requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſite in the lawe that euery ſacrefice ſhould be ſeſoned with ſalt. Even ſo ys it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, ſayeth oure ſavioure Ieſus Chriſte. that euery man, who ys alſo a ſacrefice. be ſalted with fyre, that ys to ſaye, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovethe euery man that dothe dedicate hi ſelfe vnto god, or with out faynynge doth truly imbrace the chriſtean religion, that he be ſprynkled &amp; ſalted with tribulation, I meane, that he be perſecuted &amp; beare his croſſe. This ys it truly that Chriſte teate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the when as he ſayde,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> ye ſhall haue afflyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:12546:17"/>in this worlde.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> This ys it, that. S. Paul by expreſſe wordes declare the ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. All thoſſe that wyll lyve godly in Chriſt Ieſus muſt ſuffer perſecution.</p>
            <p>This ys that purgatorye wherof. ſ. Paul dothe admonyſhe vs in his epiſtell to the Corynthes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> in theſſe wordes. Every ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s worke ſhall appare, for the day off the lorde (that ys to ſaye, the tyme off af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flyction) ſhall declare it. Which ſhalbe ſhowed in fyre, &amp; the fyre (that ys to ſaye the croſſe) ſhall trye euery mans worke what it ys. For this cauſe alſo, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor off the boke that we call Eccleſiaſticus, ſayeth.<note place="margin">Eccle. 2.</note>My ſonne when thow comeſt into the ſeruyce off God, kepe thy ſelfe in ryghtouſnes and fere, &amp; prepare thy ſoull to ſuffer temptation. Wher vnto ys to be refarred the ſaynge off Ieſus Chriſt, Iff a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny man wyll folowe me,<note place="margin">Luc 9.</note> let hym renoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; forſake hym ſelfe &amp; take vp his croſſe and folowe me. For as he ſayeth in. S. Mathew,<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> be that dothe not take vp his croſſe, &amp; folowe me, ys not worthy off me. What ys that to ſaye? He ys not worthy off me? It ys to ſaye, as wytneſſeth. S. Luc, he cannot be my dyſſyple, he cannot be a chryſtean. For a chryſtean beleve the
<pb facs="tcp:12546:17"/>a chriſtean hopethe, a chriſtean lovethe, a chriſtea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffrethe gladly for the glory off God, and who ſo euer dothe not ſo, he ys no thynge leſſe than a chriſtean. Behold here trow, my brytherin &amp; moſt dere fryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, behold I ſaye the ordynance of God, behold alſo what the moſt certayne &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcryptures dothe teache conſeruynge oure eſtate. And truly all vertyous and godly men that haue byn ſyns the begy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, haue perfe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly taſted and felte, the effycacie &amp; power of this diuine ordinance, which ys all to gyther voyde off mutaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And they haue knowen by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the truther off Godes worde, which promiſeth vnto vs in this worlde no thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge but the croſſe,<note place="margin">Act. 14.</note> ſaynge that by many tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bulations we muſt enter into the kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off heaven. But how and wherin haue they felte the power off this his prouiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce? How haue they experimented the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte off this his holy worde? Well I nought. For all they to gyther with out any exception haue byn afflycted &amp; yll en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated off the wordlynges. The which thynge to be trewe,<note place="margin">Iudeth. 8.</note> the holy woman Iude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the dothe witneſſe the ſame vnto vs in hyr boke, where as ſhe ſayethe: All the fayght
<pb facs="tcp:12546:18"/>full that in tyme paſt haue pleaſed God, haue paſſed by many tribulations. And yff ye ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to beholde the examples off theyre lyffe, Ye ſhall fynde no thynge more certayne.<note place="margin">Gene. 4. Math. 23.</note> Tell me I pray you? Abel, whom Ieſus Chriſt calleth ryghtous, was he not perſecuted? When as his ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne brother dyd moſt cruelly morther him. Noye, who a wholl yere to gyther was incloſed in the arke vpon the waters,<note place="margin">Gene. 7.</note> with all ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner off beaſres, &amp; a none after was deryded off his owne naturall ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne,<note place="margin">Rom. 4. Gene. 12.13.14.20.22 23. Gene. 19.</note> had he no tribulation? Abraham, whom. S. Paul callethe the father (that ys to ſaye the example) off all belevers, taſted he no adverſyte? Alas he never had here any other thynge. Loth alſo his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>weu, ſuffred he no iniure 11. Sodome? Iſaac, had he not a great and marvelous temptation when as at the comaundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t off God,<note place="margin">Gene. 22.</note> Abraham his father, who lo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved hym ſo tenderly, toke hym &amp; bounde hym,<note place="margin">Gene. 27</note> to make hym a ſacrefice? Iacob, was he not moleſied &amp; affacted by his bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther Eſau, when as he thrratened to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yll hym?<note place="margin">Gene. 37.39.</note> And Ioſeph, how was be entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted off his brytherin, what iniure reſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed he by a laſſyvyous woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who falſlie
<pb facs="tcp:12546:18"/>accuſed hym off adulterye? But this croſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe was the meanes off his exaltation and prefarme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And of Moyſes, what ſhal we ſaye, it ſhal ſuffice to reherſe, that which ys wrytten of hym in the epiſtell to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> breus. To wyt,<note place="margin">Hebr 11. Exod. 12.</note> when Moyſes was great, by fayght he refuſed to be called the ſonne off Pharaos doughter, &amp; choſſe rather to ſuffer aduerſite with the people off God, then to enioye the pleaſures off ſynne for a ſeaſon, &amp; extemed the rebuke off Chriſte greater ryches, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the treaſures of Egyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te O Moyſes, the trew ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t off God, thow dydeſt then conſyder, that thynge, which ſyns the holy goſt hathe vttred by the mouthe off Salomon kynge off Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem, namly,<note place="margin">prouer, 16</note> It is better to be perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the humble, then to part the ſpoylle with the prowde &amp; arrogant.</p>
            <p>O that thow wart then byrectly led with that ſpiret, who ſyns thy tyme hath ſayd vnto vs. I had rather be a dore keper i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the howſſe of God then to dwell in the taber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacles off the vnryghtous, that ys to ſaye I had rather beare the croſſe with the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple off God, then to raigne &amp; tryumphe with his enymes, O godly mynde, O di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vine and chriſtean affection. But let vs
<pb facs="tcp:12546:19"/>retorne to oure matter. Ioſua the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſor off Moyſes,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 1.10.</note> (to whoſſe voyce the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de God obayed whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſtayed the courſe off the Sonne) dyd he enter into the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de off promys with out croſſe &amp; tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?<note place="margin">Iudh. 4.</note> The ſcriptures recorde the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary.</p>
            <p>And Debora beynge a moſt vertuous woman, &amp; moſt iuſtly governynge the people off God, had not the aduerſite, as well as the other? Yea that ſhe had, and yet not wyt ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge ſhe ſhowed hyr ſelfe more vertuous &amp; worthy, then the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off hyr tyme. The lorde gyve now vnto wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the hart of Sebora. Alſo Ierobaal o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyffe called Gedeon,<note place="margin">Iudg. 6.</note> was he exemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted from aduerſyte? I report me to the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke off the Iudges. Lykwyffe Sampſon whom the lorde had blyſhed,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.</note> was not he afflycted by the philiſtians, who puttyng out his eyes, they made theyre foule off hym? Saynt Paul in the <hi>.13.</hi> chapter off the Ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es beare the wytnes, that God found Dauid a man after his owne har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. And yet not withſtandyng all the lyffe of Dauid well conſydered,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 19 20 21.22. 2. Sam. 15</note> was no thynge els but trouble, afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; aduerſite. What ſuffred he at the hande off Saul? What ſuffred he by his ſonne Abſolon, whom he
<pb facs="tcp:12546:19"/>loued ſo enterely? Yea he ſuffred ſo many thynges &amp; ſo grevous to be borne, that it cannot be expreſſed. And yet in this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall croſſe, in theſſe quotidian afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in theis contyneuall torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes as well of the ſoull as of the bodye, how dyd Dauid behaue hym ſelfe? What ſayd he? He ſayd, I am redy, that the lorde do with me, as it ſemethe vnto hym beſt. I am redy to beare paciently &amp; with a good wyll all that it ſhall pleaſe hym to ſende me. O ſaynge worthy off recordation in the hart off a chriſtian. O voyce all to gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heavenly. O fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe perfytly beaten downe, or rather all to gyther mortyfyed by the myghty mallet and power off the ſprete, able to ouerthrowe mountaynes. To the which ſaynge agreethe the wordes of Hely the preſt.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.</note> To whom when Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el had ſhewed the rewyne off his howſſe, he anſwered, He ys the lorde, let hym do, what it beſt ſemeth vnto hym. O that the Soules off thoſſe men are moſt fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, whoſe carnall affections and fleſly cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the fyre off Godes ſpirete hath ſo perfytly conſumed, and brought to this pas, that they can willingly ſaye vnto the lorde there God, O God thow art maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:12546:20"/>do with vs what ſo euer is pleaſeth the, thy will be done. But theſſe men before menſioned, dyd they for al theyre perſecutions, at any tyme forſake the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, or be came ſlacke in well doynge? No truly,<note place="margin">Tob. 3</note> whervnto I appele as a wyttnes the good Tobias who diuers wayes was afflicted, &amp; yet not withſtandynge all his afflictions, dyd neuer forſake the waye off verite and truthe. I produce alſo to witnes the fayghtfull Iob, off whom ye haue hard the affliction and pacience.<note place="margin">Iob. 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What ſaye ye alſo to al the prophetes who haue borne a bout the worde off verite? We will ſaye off them that which Ieſus Chriſt dothe teache vs, when as he ſayed vnto his diſſiples, and in them to vs.</p>
            <p>Blyſſed are ye, when men revyle you, &amp; ſaye all manner off evell ſaynges agaynſt you for my names ſake,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> reioyſe &amp; beglad, for great ys your reward in heaven, for ſo perſecuted they the prophetes which were before you. But what? dyd they perſecute ſome of the prophetes, and lefte other ſome vn afflicted? No. They haue vniuerſally perſecuted them all, with out any exception. The which thynge to be trew, ys evydent by the wordes off. S.
<pb facs="tcp:12546:20"/>Sthephen.<note place="margin">Act. 7.</note> Which off the prophetes ys there (ſayth he) whom your fathers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not perſecuted, from the fyrſt vnto the laſt. And not only the prophetes, but Iohn alſo, who was more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a prophet, even ſuche a one (as wytneſſeth Ieſus Chriſt) as there was not a greater borne a mongeſt the childeren off women.<note place="margin">Math. 11</note> Ther was no prophet greater then Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſie, and yet was he perſecuted. But how was he perſecured? They dyd vnto hym all to gyther what ſo euer they wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and yet was he that Helias as teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth Ieſus Chriſt that was promyſed to come.<note place="margin">Math. 17</note> Here we haue no ſmall occaſion to ſtaye oure ſelves, &amp; diligently to conſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the profounde and admirable Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment off the lorde. For. S. Iohn was a moſt holy and vertuous man, he ſought in all thynges the glory off God, he neuer dyd iniure to any man lyvynge, he was a man all to gyther inreprehenſible. And yet all this not withſtandynge, the lorde gave hym ouer into the handes of his eny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, to erecute theyre tyrannye vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym,<note place="margin">Math. 3. Marc. 1. Iohn. 1.</note> the which thynge alſo he moſt paciently ſuffred. Ought we then to be abaſhed &amp; marvayll yff he ſuffer vs wreched ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="tcp:12546:21"/>to faull into the handes off oure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaryes &amp; capitall enymes? Or rather how myche ovght we hyghly to thanke hym, for his gentyll correction, &amp; paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently endure theſame. Truly my fryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des it ys oure duty ſo to do. But it ys but a ſmall thynge that the enymes off the faygh dyd vnto ſaynt Iohn, all thought they dyd what ſo ever they coulde. For they dyd vnto Ieſus Chriſt the ſoune off God, what ſo ever they wolde, As he hym ſelfe propheſied before in ſaynt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, ſaynge,<note place="margin">Math. 17</note> I ſaye vnto you, that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias ys come all redy, &amp; they knew hym not, but haue done vnto hym what ſo ev<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> they luſted, in lykewyſſe alſo ſhal the ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne off man ſuffer off them. But who ys this ſonne off man? The ſonne off man in this place ys to ſaye the ſonne off God,<note place="margin">Math. 1</note> the only &amp; trew Meſſias, that ys to ſaye the only &amp; trew ſavioure off the worlde, to be breffe, it ys Ieſus Chriſt hym ſelf who ſpake it, who o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly a boue all other ys moſt worthy to be called man, or the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne off man, not by cauſe off his humylyte and abiection, not by cauſe he ys not bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne off man and woman as other ate, but for by cauſe that he only (who ys bothe
<pb facs="tcp:12546:21"/>God and man) ys the honoure, the glorie, and the perfyte ſavyoure off the humay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne nature, for it ys he only that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payred and reſtored theſame agayne into his perfection, it ys he that makethe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, perfyte men, for with out hym, man ys, no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that ys to ſaye, the image of god, but a beaſte &amp; worſe then a beaſte, yea the perfyte image of the devell. And this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this ſonne off man, who only ys the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte man,<note place="margin">Math. 1.</note> and alſo (Emmanuel) that ys to ſaye God with vs, and conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly the glorye of man, was gyven into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of ſynners, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that they myght do with hym what ſo euer they wolde, that ys to ſaye, what ſo euer God his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther had before ordayned off hym to be do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne: and they dyd it. Now my brytherin and fryndes I do demande off you? Yff God the eternall father hath not ſpared his owne proper ſonne, as ſayeth Gaynt Paul, but hathe abandoned hym to the wyll off ſynners. Ought we to thynke it ſtrange yff he do gyve vs into the han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des off ſynners, (we wiche are alſo ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) to thende we may be made confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable and lyke vnto his ſonne,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> accordig to his determination before the fondati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:12546:22"/>off the earthe. And tell me, I beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che you, ys a ſholler abone his maſter, or a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t greater then his lorde whom he ſeruethe? Or rather ought not the ſkol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to be contented when as he ys intrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted as his maſter, and the ſeruant as his lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de. Gyve eare I praye to a worthy ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that a certayne chriſtean hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in oure tyme.</p>
            <p>O ſaruantes, do ye thynke, that it beho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the you to reſt and take youre eaſe, when as the lorde dothe trauaylle &amp; take payne? Truly all the faughfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes and good chriſteans that were in the tyme off Ieſus chriſt, and alſo ſyns his deathe, haue had no reſte, but haue all wayes trabyled: they haue all byn per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuted, as was theyr maſter: wheroff he warned them alſo beforre hande,<note place="margin">Marh. 10. Mar. 13.</note> ſaynge, yff they haue perſecuted me, even ſo wyll they perſecute you. Wherfor yff the worlde dyd make warre agaynſt the maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ys it reaſon that we his ſeruantes ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> peace and pleaſure? Or rather ys it poſſible that we ſhould not ſuffer, ſeyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the maſter hath ſuffred? Who euer knewe the members in healthe, &amp; the hea de ſycke? who euer harde off any ſhuche
<pb facs="tcp:12546:22"/>ſhynge? And forther more yff the pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce hym ſelfe go vnto the warres for the co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men wealthe off his contrye: ys he not al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to gyther a cowarde and a daſtard, that ſekethe hys eaſe at home, and wyll not accompany his prince, who willyngly de the abandon hym ſelfe to emyne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t danger for the vtilite off the comen wealthe. Bow myche more, yff the ſonne off God,<note place="margin">Ebr. 12.</note> who ys oure only prince be in his owne perſon in the batayll, armed at all poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, are we fayghfull ſeruantes, are we worthy ſoldiours, are we trew chriſteans, yff we do not accompany hym? And yff all ouer companyons be about oure prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, berynge the brounte off the battayll with hym, and we tarrynge behynde, do we not meryte to be erpulſed his ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; felowſbyppe, to be raſed ont off the boke off lyffe, and to be reprobated and accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for euer? Truly, we deſerue no thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge els, and then ſo ſhall it happen vnto vs. Barken I beſyche you, what the angell off the lorde God ſayeth in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke off the iudges. Curſe ye the Lyte of Meros (ſayeth the angell of the lorde, curſe the inhabiters therof, by cauſe they came not forthe to helpe the lorde, neyther
<pb facs="tcp:12546:23"/>to helpe the myghty. Here may ye ſe a moſt certayne malediction and curſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on ſhuche as are ſlacke and neclegent to aſſyſt the lorde in the tyme off tribulation. In tyme paſt alſo when Gedeon made warre agaynſt the Madianites, he lefte be hynde hym and dyd not call the men off Ephraim to aſſyſt hym, wher for they we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re grevouſlye offended with hym,<note place="margin">Iudg. 7.</note> &amp; kend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyd in ſhuche indignation, that it wanted lytell that they had not oultraged &amp; dyſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royed hym. Why haſt thow ſerued vs thus (ſayed they) that thow calledeſt vs not with the, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thow wenteſt to fyght with the Madianites? Ye may ſe that the men of Ephraim, dyd not deſyre to tarry at home &amp; ſeke theyr eaſe, when as theyr captayne Gedion with his armye was in perryll and in danger off the ennymes.</p>
            <p>Lykwyſe we reade in the boke off Samu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>el,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 11</note> that when David kynge off Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was aduertiſed that Harſabe the wyffe off Vryas was with childe. He ſent vnto his cheffe captayne Ioab, &amp; commanded hym, to ſend him Vryas, who was as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the campe amongeſt the other captay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; ſoldiours off the kynge. When V<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryas was come, and after the kynge had
<pb facs="tcp:12546:23"/>inquyred off him the eſtate off his armye, he ſayd to Vryas, go into thy howſſe, &amp; waſhe thy fette. And Vryas (as ſayeth the hyſtorye) departed out of the kynges howſſe, and there followed hym a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce ffrom the kynges table.</p>
            <p>But Vryas ſlepte at the gate off the kynges pallace with other off his lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſeruantes, and went not downe into his howſſe: off the which thynge, when kynge Dauid was informed, he ſayed to Vryas, are not thow come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fylde? why then doeſt not thow go downe into thy howſſe? But now I beſyche you brytheren, gyve eare and conſyder dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, the worthy anſwer off Vrias, the which truly ys worthy off perpetuall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, and neuer to be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>But what ſayde he? The arck off God &amp; Iſraell &amp; Iuda dwell in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes (ſayeth he) my lord Ioab, and the ſeruantes off my lorde, lye vpon the face of the earthe, and ſhall I then go into myn howſſe, to eate and dryncke, &amp; to lye with my wyffe? for thy healthe and for the healthe of thy Soule I wyll not do this thynge. O moſte excellent, whorthy, and vertious man. O conſtant mynde neuer werye
<pb facs="tcp:12546:24"/>off troble and payne. O ſaynge neuer to be forgotten. For he wold not take his caſe, when it was tyme to travayll: but wolde go with the reſt, &amp; beare his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te off the burden. Ys it lawfull the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for vs, brytherin, to ſeke oure eaſe, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſuffer, ſeynge that all oure compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyons haue ſuffred, and do ſuffer, &amp; alſo our only hedd Ieſus Chriſt with them? There ys no apparant excuſe why we ſhoulde do ſo.<note place="margin">Iphe 2.4 Iom. 12.</note> Wherfor David in his ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſpekynge in the perſon off Chriſte, &amp; off his myſtycall bodye, that ys to ſaye, of vs, he ſayd, I am ordayned to be wypped and beaten. And. S. Peter in his fyrſt epiſtell ſayeth the lyke.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> Yff for well doyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge (ſayeth he) ye ſuffer wronge, and take it pacyently then ys there thanke with God, for there vnto veryly were ye cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Conſyder erneſtly, derely beloved theſſe. <hi>2.</hi> ſentences. Dauid affirmethe that we are ordayned to be afflicted, and G. Peter ſayethe that we are called to ſuffer. Namly to ſuffer paciently, &amp; that for ryghtouſnes ſake.<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> Ys there any excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe then, why we ſhould refuſe paciently to ſuffer for ryghtouſnes ſake, ſeynge we are there vnto ordayned and called of god?
<pb facs="tcp:12546:24"/>Ought we to refuſe, wyllyngly to dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke off that cupe that God our father hath ordayned and gyven vnto der that we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re no perfyte obedience to the diuine ordy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance.<note place="margin">Math. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> That were no dyrecte followyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge off oure vocation. That were no trew expreſſion off the example off the ſonne off God oure only hope.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2</note> That were no thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge confirmable vnto this order of prayer, Oure father thy will be done. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that were no waye to declare oute ſelfes to be chriſteans, but rather to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſt our ſelves enymes and aduerſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes to the moſt holy and tyghtons wyll off God: Yea it were no thynge els but dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to mourmure agaynſt God. It ys written in the boke of Iudgethe, how that thoſſe that reſayved not the temptatione,<note place="margin">Iudg. 8.</note> with the fere off God, but put them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe forthe with vnpaciencye and murmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge agaynſt God, peryſhed off the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troyer, and were ſlayne off ſerpentes. Do we thynke then to eſcape the extermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ponyſhment off God yff we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come murmorers &amp; repyners agaynſt his determinate ordinance &amp; pleaſure? In ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge meanes to avoyde the croſſe, which he dothe preſent vnto vs, for the glorie of
<pb facs="tcp:12546:25"/>his name, and oure commodite? Alas O lorde,<note place="margin">Act. 5. Gal 6. 2. tim. 4.</note> ſo miſerable ys oure eſtate &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyſſion, and ſo greatly doth it dyffer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure Anceſters and fathers. For the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtels and fyrſte chriſteans, dyd reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, when God dyd them this honoure, as to ſuffer iniurye &amp; perſecution ffor the name off Ieſus Chriſte. And they dyd not reioyſe with out a cauſe,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> for as mythe as the ſcripture ſaye the. Blyſſed are ye, yff ye ſuffer any thynge for ryghtouſnes ſake, eya blyſſed are ye when me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> revyle you, and perſecute you, and ſhall falſly ſaye all manner off evell ſaynges agaynſt you for my ſake, reioyſe and be glad, for great ys your reward in heaven, that ys to ſaye, the kyngdom of heaven ys yours, as he ſayd a lytell before. Blyſſed are theſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that ſuffer perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ryghtouſnes ſake, for theyrs ys the kyngdom off hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Theſſe confortable wordes &amp; ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of oure ſavyoure Ieſus Chriſt, beynge fyrinly imbraced and credyted off the apoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>telles and prymatyve chriſteans, moved them boldly and ſtoutly to imbrace the croſſe, in willyngly ſubmittynge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnder the ſame. For they had a meſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne aſſurance founded vpon the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent
<pb facs="tcp:12546:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>verytable worde off the ſonne off God.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> That in ſo doynge they were happy and blyſſed, and that they ſhould haue parte in the conſolations, &amp; glorye off Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, as thei had participated with hym in his tribulations. But are we chriſteans of theſſe dayes, come to this Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſew? Haue we avanſed oure ſelfes ſo far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re? or do we as they dyd? Alas, no. The lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be mercyfull vnto vs. For that curſed loue of oure ſelues, ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth in vs the love off God. And the affection that we haue vnto fryvolous and tranſitore thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges that are permanent and eternall) do cauſe vs to haue in hatred,<note place="margin">Math. 10.16.20. Mat. 8. Luc. 9</note> the perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and croſſe, which the ſonne off God hym ſelfe hath with ſaffed to beare, before vs, and for vs. And what may be the cauſe heroff, I pray you? But only oure incre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dulyte for that we do not fyrmly beleve the worde off God, which his owne ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne hath moſt fayghtfully teſtified vnto vs. This vicious loue, and this damna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble affection, which doth ſo drawe vs, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thynges where vnto we are called, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they proſede from any other thynge, then
<pb facs="tcp:12546:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>from a diffidence and myſtruſt that we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue in the ſaynges and promyſes of the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne off God? I report me to your conſyer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Truly the apoſtles and prymatyve churche who were perfyte chriſteans. And dyd fayghtfully beleue the ſaynges of the ſonne of God. They dyd not governe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes on this ſorte, but ſuffred gladly for Ieſus Chriſt, and for the teſtimonye of his goſpell, when it pleaſed the good will off God, that they ſhould be afflicted. They dyd neuer diſſwade one another to ſuffer, but contrary wyſſe, they dyd anymate &amp; bolden one another even to the very dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. Paraduenture ye wyll anſwer me, and ſaye, all this ys trew, we acknowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. But the croſſe off the Apoſtles and off the fyrſt chryſteans, was not ſo hard, ſo cruell, nor ſo evell to be borne: As ys the croſſe that God layeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in theſſe dayes. Wherfor they bare theyre croſſe eaſely, and we wyth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re payne. O vnadvyſed ſaynge, O obiec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion worthy off reproffe. Do we ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe that the croſſe off the Apoſtles and pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue chriſteans, was eaſy to be borne? I praye you, let vs take the payne, to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyder what was theyre croſſe, and that do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne,
<pb facs="tcp:12546:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>we ſhall eaſely deſerne which ys the more grev uſer. Trulye yff we wolde with a ſyngle eye conſyder all thynges, we ſhould fynde that we al togyther dyd new ſuffer the tenthe part of the payne &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that. S. Paul hym ſelfe only dyd taſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and endure. And therfor dothe he boſte hym ſelfe, that he ys a better ſeruant off Ieſus Chriſt, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were, a certayne kynde off falls prophetes amongeſt the Corrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, off when he maketh menſion. Wherfor yff it pleaſe you, let vs here him ſelfe ſpeake.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note> 
               <q>They are the miniſters off Chriſt (ſayeth he) I am more, in labours more abondant, in ſtrypes aboue meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, in priſon more plentiouſe, in peryll off death often, off the Iewes fyve tymes reſſayved I forty ſtrypes ſaue one, thriſſe was I beaten with roddes, I was ons ſtoned, I ſuffred thryſſe ſhypwrake, nyght and day haue I byn in the depe ſee, in ior<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neynge often, in perylles off waters, in perylles of robbers, in ieoperdes of myn owne nation, in ieoperdes amongeſt the heathen, in perylles in the Cyte, in peryl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in the wildernes, in perylles in the ſea in perylles amongeſt fals brytherin, in la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour &amp; travayll, in watchynge often, in
<pb facs="tcp:12546:27"/>honger &amp; thyrſt, in faſtynge often, in col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; nakednes, beſyde the thiges that out wardly happen vnto me.</q> Here may you ſe, what ſaynt Paul dyd ſuffer ffor the teſtimonie off Ieſus Chriſte.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> And in an other place he ſayethe. Britherin I woul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de not have you ignorant, off oure trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble which happened vnto vs in Aſia, for we were greued out off meaſure paſſyng ſtrength ſo greatly that we dyſpayred even off lyffe. Alſo we reſſayved an anſwer off deathe in oure ſelfes, that we ſhould not put oure truſt in oure ſelfes, but in god, which raiſethe the dead to lyffe agay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, and which delyuered vs from ſo great a deathe, and dothe delyuer, on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we truſt, that yet here after he will delyver, by the helpe off your prayers for vs, that by the meanes off many perſons, thankes may begyuen off many on oure behalfe, for the gifte gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs. Here may ye ſe (my fryndes) here maye ye ſe the croſſe off Saynt Paul, here may ye ſe what he hath ſuffred, and yet this ys not all. For he hath ſuffred manye other thynges as wytneſſethe the boke off the Actes off the Apoſtles, and fynally be ſuffred deathe for the witneſſynge off Ieſus Chriſt. For there more. S. Paul hath not only made
<pb facs="tcp:12546:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ncion, off that which he dyd ſuffer hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe, but alſo he hath made reherſall off the eſtate off the other apoſtles off his ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Wherfor, for Godes ſake harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what he ſayeth off them to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> Truly I beleue (ſayeth he) that god hath ſet vs forthe, (we which are the laſt apoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tels) as it were men appoynted to deathe, for we are a gaſyng ſtocke vnto the worlde, and to the angelles &amp; to men, we are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les for chryſtes ſake, but ye are wyſſe through chriſte. We are weake, but ye are ſtronge. Ye are honorable, but we are dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyſed.</p>
            <p>Even vnto this tyme we hounger and thurſte and are naked and are buffyted with fyſtes, and haue no certayne dwellyng place, and labour workynge with oure owne handes. We are reuyled, and yet we blyſſe, we are per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuted, and ſuffer it, we are evell ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off, and we praye, we are made as it were the fylthynes off the worlde and the off, ſcowrynge off all thynges even vnto this daye. That ys to ſaye we are no leſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable vnto the worlde, then were thoſſe that the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tylles dyd cuſtomablye throwe into the watter for the preſeruation off the commen wealthe. And in a nother
<pb facs="tcp:12546:28"/>place he ſaythe. We are troubled on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſyde, yet are we not forſaken, we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in povertye, but yet not vtterly with out ſome what, We ſuffer perſecution, but are not relynquythed therin. We are caſt downe, neuertheleſſe we peryſhe not. We all wayes beare about in our bodyes the mortification of the lorde Ieſus, that the lyffe off Ieſus myght appere in oure bodyes, for we which lyde, are all wayes delyvered vnto deathe for Ieſus ſake, that the lyffe off Ieſus myght alſo appere in oure mortall fleſhe. Now haue ye har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de what. S. Paul teſtifyeth off his eſtate and off the other apoſtles. Now I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyche you gyne eare vnto that he wryte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the off the eſtate off all the ſayntes in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, that is to ſaye off all the electe &amp; trew chylderin of God by Ieſus Chriſte. Throught fayght (ſayeth he) they haue ſubdewed kyngdomes,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.</note> wrought ryghtouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, obtayned the promys, ſtopped the mouthes off lyons, quenched the violence off fyre, eſcaped the edge off the ſworde, out off weaknes they were made ſtronge, waxed valiant in fyght, turned to flyght the armes off the aliantes, the wyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayded theyre dead to lyffe agayne: Other
<pb facs="tcp:12546:28"/>were racked &amp; woulde not be delyvered, that they myght inheryte a better reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: Agayne other were tryed with mockynges and ſkornynges, more ov<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan> with bondes, and priſonment, were ſtoned, were hewen a ſonder, were tempted, we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſlayne with the ſworde, walked vp and downe in ſhepſkyns, and gotſkyns, beyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge deſtitute, troubled and vexed, they wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred in wyldernes, in mountaynes and in caves off the earthe, off which me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the worlde was not worthy off. Beholde the lyffe, beholde the eſtate and intretyng off the childerin off God, durynge the ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me they were in this worlde, Ys there any greater te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations, then theſſe which we haue hard reherſed? And yet neuer the leſſe Ieſus Chriſt and his membres before vs haue ſuffred them. But in all theſſe extreme temptations how dyd they beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue them ſelves? Were they at ony tyme aſtoyned or dyſcomforted? No, truly. As wytneſſeth. S. Paul, ſaynge. Blyſſed be God the ffather off oure Lord Ieſus Chriſte which ys the father off mercye &amp; God off all conſolation,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> which confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs in all our tribulations in ſo myche that we are able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort them that are
<pb facs="tcp:12546:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12546:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12546:30"/>in any manner of trouble, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame comfort, that we oure ſelfes are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted off God, for as the afflictions off Chriſt are plentious in vs: even ſo ys our conſolation plentious by Chriſte.<note place="margin">Cor. 12.</note> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayeth in a nother place. Therfor wyll I very gladly reioyſſe in myn infirmites that the ſtrenght off Chriſt may dwell in me, Therfor haue I my delectation, in infirmites and in rebukes, in neceſſites, in perſecutions and in anguyſhes for chriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes ſake, for when I am weake, then am I ſtronge. Here by it ys apparant that G. Paul was not dyſeomforted not dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corraged in the middes off his tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but ſuffred all thynges very gladly &amp; quy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, even very deathe for the teſtimony of the truthe: he wold not alſo that his frin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſhould be moued or troubled for any thynge that myght happen vnto hym, but rather that they ſhould reioyſe with him. The which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable leſſon he truly ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the moſt floryſhynge ſkolle off his maſter Ieſus Chriſt, who ſayed vnto his dyſſiples, Let not your hartes be greved, neyther fere, ye haue hard how I ſayed vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> I go and come agayne vnto you, yff ye loued me ye wold verely reioyſe, by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:12546:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>I go vnto my father. The which thinge truly the diſſiples dyd ſhowe in the ende, that they dyd love hym vnfaynedly: For after that he was viſibley departed from them as towchynge his bodyly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and aſſended vp into the heavens, wheras he remaynethe reſedent vnto this hower, lyvynge and raignynge &amp; prayng for vs. They retorned vnto Ieruſalem with great ioye and gladnes as teſtyfyeth G. Luc.<note place="margin">Act. 1.</note> But dyd Paul and the other apoſtles only reioyſſe in tribulation? Al the other chriſteans who haue ſuffred for the veryte ſake, dyd not they alſo reioyſſe in beringe theyre croſſe. Yeas, truly, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto oure god. The which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge. G. Paul, ſpeki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge as wel of other as of hym ſelfe dothe ſufficiently declare, ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. We do not only glory, in the glore off the ſonne of God, but alſo we do glorie in tribulation. As who wold ſaye, we chriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teans are not off that opinion, that the worldly men are of, for worldly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and deteſte all tribulations, &amp; call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> evelles, Thynkyng it an evell, odious &amp; ſhamfull thynge to ſuffer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But contrarywyſſe the trew chriſteans, do glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye and reioyſſe in all theyre perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. That ys to ſaye they are aſſured that they
<pb facs="tcp:12546:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>re perſecutions, make for theyre glorye, honeſtye, wealthe, vtilite, and ſynguler profyte: For the which cauſe they do glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in ſuffrynge,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.</note> and do reioyſſe. For. G Iames in the name off God dothe coman<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de them to do ſo, ſaynge. My brytherin extyme it an excedyng ioye, when you fal into dyuers temptations.<note place="margin">1. pet. 4.</note> G. Peter al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo exhorteth them vnto theſame thynge, when he ſayethe, dearly beloued maruell not that ye are provyd by fyre (which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ys to trye you) as thought ſome ſtran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge thynge happyned vnto you: But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyſſe, in as myche as ye are pertakers of chriſtes paſſions, that when his glory ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perethe, ye may be mery and glade. For truly all chriſteans, yff they be in very de de chriſteans, do not only reioyſſe &amp; glorye in theyre tribulations, but alſo they gyve harty thankes vnto God, &amp; therin prayſſe his holy name. In which doynge they folowe the example off the .iij. chylderin that beinge throwen into the fornace, bounde,<note place="margin">Dany. 3.</note> walkynge in the myddes off a great fyre, dyd gyve thankes, prayſe and glorifye the lorde. They alſo folowe the example off Iob,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> who ſayed, yff we haue reſſayued good thynges at the handes off
<pb facs="tcp:12546:31"/>God, why not e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell alſo? The lorde hath gyven, and the lorde hath taken awaye, even as it pleaſethe the lorde, ſo ys it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to pas, blyſſed be the name off the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. S. Peter alſo dothe gyve them in comandment to do the lyke, ſaynge,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> Yff ye be rayled vpon for the name off Chriſte happye are ye, for the glorye and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit off God reſteth vpon you, but ſe that none off you do ſuffer as a mortherer, or as a theefe, or an evell doer, or as a buſy body in other mens matters, yff any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffer as a chriſtean, let hym not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, but let hym glorifye God on his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halffe. But wherfor ys it, that the chriſteans, do ſo greatly reioyſe in theyre tribulations? And do gyve thankes and prayſſe the name off God in the myddes off theyre afflictions? G. Paul in his E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſtell to the Romaynes dothe gyve vs a playne reſolution theroff in theſſe wordes We knowe (fayeth he) that tribulation bryngethe pacyence,<note place="margin">Roma. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> pacience bryngethe ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perience, experience bryngethe hope, &amp; hope maketh vs not aſhamed, by cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe the love off God ys ſhede a brode <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hartes, by the holy goſte which ys gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vnto vs. What meanethe this ſayn
<pb facs="tcp:12546:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>Tribulation bryngethe pacyence? ys) it the nature off tribulation to make all men pacient indifferently, that are afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and troubled? (No truly.) For yff tribulation naturallye dyd worke pacien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in all them that are troubled, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be all men generallye paciently heare they<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re tribulations. But euery one dothe not ſo. For we do ſe at thys tyme the moſt part off men mourmer and grudge with out a cauſe, and folyſlye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playne in they<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re afflictions and aduerſites. What ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue I done (ſaye they)? Wherin haue I offended? Lan theſſe wordes proſede fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a pacient harte that willyngly dothe ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myte hym ſelfe vnder the moſt iuſt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment off God? It ys certayne that it can not. And therfor it ſemethe that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtell, here ſpeke the agaynſt the experien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce that we haue off thynges. But on the otherſyde yf we do dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly waye to who me he here ſpekethe, namly vnto the chriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teans, he beynge alſo a chriſtean, we ſhal eaſely gather, where vnto the tendethe.</p>
            <p>For it behoueth vs to conſyder and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande that the tribulations whereoff he now treatethe, are not the tribulations off the worldlynges. But rather they are
<pb facs="tcp:12546:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>the tribulations off the electe and trew childerin off God, whoſſe properiyes he here declarethe, and ſayeth. What tribula<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion (that ys to ſaye) the tribulation off o chriſtean, bryngethe pacyence. But, which waye? A chriſtean man that ſeethe hym ſelfe troubled and afflicted, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth forth with that his tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dothe not happen to him by fortune or chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for he ys not off that vnhappy and dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable feet off infideles that bare denye the diuine prouidence off God, laying as we reade in the boke of Ieremyes lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s That from the mouthe off the lorde proſe dethe neyther good not evell.<note place="margin">Lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 3.</note> The lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſeethe vs not,<note place="margin">Ezech. 9.</note> he hath forſaken the ear the. And as it ys writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the boke of Iob. Tuſhe, how ſhould God knowe? dothe his dominion reache beyonde the cloudes?<note place="margin">Iob. 22.</note> Tuſhe, the cloudes cover hym that he may not ſe, for he dwelle the aboue the ſcyrcie off the heavens. All theſſe wordes or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blaſphemes, ſignifye no thynge els, nor tende to none other ende, but to make vs beleve, that God, that hath made hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven and ear the doth not entermedel with humayne and earthely thynges, And that it ys not he that ſendethe vnto man good
<pb facs="tcp:12546:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>and evell, proſperite &amp; aduerſite, which we taſt in this lyffe. But a trew chriſte and doth not gyve any credyte vnto ſo peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and diabolicall a lye. For, to thynk off God, a thynge ſo myche vnworthy his maieſtye ys not the worke off a chriſtean, but off an Epicurian or of an Ariſtoteler. <q>A chriſtean man gyvethe reuerence vnto the worde off God, in belevynge &amp; fyrm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dwellyng vpon the ſame, all thought al the vniuerſall worlde wolde contenſiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye affirme the contrarye.</q> And the worde off God ſayethe. <hi>Tua pater proui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dentia ab initio cuncta gubernat.</hi> O fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (ſayethe the ſcripture) thy prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce gouernethe all thynge from the begy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge. And agayne if ſayethe. Who ys he there that ſayethe that any thynge ys done, with out the comandment off the lorde. Forther more the lorde our God ſpekynge by the mouthe of the prophet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaias ſaye the.<note place="margin">Eſai. 45.</note> I am the lorde, and there ys none other beſyde me, fformynge the lyght, and creatyng the darcknes, makyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge peace, and creatynge evell, yea I am the lorde that dothe al theſſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges ſayeth the all myghty God.<note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> And in Seutrend he ſayethe, behold, I am the God alone,
<pb facs="tcp:12546:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>and there ys none but I. I kyll and wyll make alyve agayne, I wounde and I wyll heale agayne. And alſo Tobias ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge reſpect vnto this ſentence, ſayed vnto the lorde, Great art thow (o ſorde) for euer more, and thy kyngdome worlde with o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ende, for thow ſkourgeſt, &amp; hea leſte thow leadeſt vnto hell, and bryngeſt out agayne, and there ys none that maye eſcape thy hande. Where vnto agreethe the author off the Eccleſiaſticus ſaynge,<note place="margin">Eccle. 11.</note> proſperite &amp; aduerſyte, lyffe and deathe pouertye and ryches, come all off the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. And to that ende dothe the prophet Amos enquyre ſaynge, Dothe there any evel happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the cyte,<note place="margin">Amos. 3.8.</note> that the lorde hath not wrought? Vſe thy ryches in the day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es off proſperite (ſayeth Ieſus the ſonne off Syrach) and haue pacience in the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me off aduerſite, for even as God hath made the one, even ſo hathe he made the other. All theſſe textes, and other infi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite contayned in the holy ſcriptures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ſufficiently, that the worlde ys not gouerned by forture and chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as the infideles dare affirme, and that agaynſt the evydent teſtimonie and iudgement off theire owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyences, which witneſſeth
<pb facs="tcp:12546:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnto them that the worlde ys all to gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gouerned by the only prouidence off God: And that as well ryches, as pouer tye, good and evell, that ys to ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, all tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, perſecutions, loſſes, afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, turmentes, and miſeryes that we ſuffer, doth only proſede from God, and that by the will, ordinance and comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment off God, who dothe all in all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, accordynge to the counſayll off his owne wyll. Wherfor when that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ys a chriſtean, dothe perſayve him ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe in any reſpect afflicted, in what ſort ſo euer it be, he dothe not doute, but ys cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taynly perſuaded that it ys god hym ſelfe that doth afflicte hym. In ſendyng hym that ſame tribulation that he hathe: and that all the wycked men off the worlde, yea even the develles and all other creatu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ree, that ſeme to afflycte, are no thynge els but the roddes and miniſters off his diuine will and ordinance, as it ys wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the prophet Eſaias,<note place="margin">Eſai. 10.</note> Aſſur, ys the rod of my furye, and my ſtaffe. Alſo in the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>54.</hi> chapter the lord ſayethe, Beholde I create the ſmythe that bloweth the colles in the fyre, and he maketh a weapon after his owne handy worke, and I mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo him
<pb facs="tcp:12546:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>that kylleth to dyſtroye. A chriſtean man now ys ſufficiently aſſured that his tribulation ys all to gyther a worke off God, and doth not only conſyder, that it ys God that afflictethe, but alſo the ende where vnto he tendythe by afflic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge him. But which waye ſhould he knowe it? By the ſcriptures only, for the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res doth not only moſt certaynly aſſure hym, that it ys God, that afflictethe, But alſo when that God afflictethe, he doth it not off hatred, nor for any plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure that he takethe in oure affliction, as teſtifiethe the boke off wyſoome, which ſayethe,<note place="margin">Sap. 1.</note> That God hatethe no thynge of that he hath made, neyther takethe he pleaſure in the diſtruction off the lyvyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. The which thynge alſo Tobias con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſethe in theſſe wordes, Lorde,<note place="margin">Tob. 3.</note> thow ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keſt no pleaſure in oure perdiction. The which thynge alſo the lorde hym ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firmethe by the mouthe off his prophet E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zechiel, I will not the deathe off a ſynnet (ſaeth he) but rather that he torne and lyve.<note place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note> A chriſtean man then, that beleve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the all that the ſcripture teacethe, doth not thynke that God dothe afflicte hym for any pleaſure that he taketh to ſe hym
<pb facs="tcp:12546:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuffer, (for that were the affection off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tyrant) neyther yet by cauſe he hateth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hym in any reſpecte, but rather he ys pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytly perſwaded that God afflicteth hym, by cauſe he lovethe hym. For he ſayeth hym ſelfe.<note place="margin">Prouer. 3 Ebr. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Ego quoſcunqe amo, arguo et caſtigo,</hi> that ys to ſaye, I do reprehen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and chaſten, all them that I love. I ys neceſſarye then that all thoſſe that god lovethe,<note place="margin">Apoc. 3.</note> and chefly thoſſe that he lovethe in Ieſus Chriſte, be chaſtyned. But wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for dothe he chaſtyce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Bycauſe that he lovethe them. But how myche dothe god love them? How myche leſſe dothe he love them, then he loved his only ſonne Ieſus Chriſte? He lovethe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as his chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derin for chriſtes ſake, and he that beleve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the not that, dothe denye the verite ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Ieſus Chriſte, who ſpekynge off thoſſe that throught the prechynge off the apoſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les ſhould beleve in hym, ſayed to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. O father thow haſt loved them, as thow haſt loved me. And Ieſus Chriſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how myche dothe he love them?<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.</note> Harken what he ſayethe in the goſpel of. S. Iohn. As my father hathe loved me,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> (ſayeth he) even ſo do I love you. O aſſured promys, O ſaynge off great conſolation,
<pb facs="tcp:12546:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>to all thoſſe that fayghtfully beleve the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame. O co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable wordes which beynge well vnderſtanded and ſurely fyxed in a chriſtean mans hart by the excellent and ſupernaturall ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer off fayght, ys able with one only blowe to ſubdew oure cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte nature, and naturall inclination, in makynge theſame willyngly obedient, to the good will off God, who hath ſo myche loved vs, and of his mere goodnes hathe done ſo myche, and hath ſuffred ſo myche for vs. But now, ſeynge that love, yea &amp; that an infinite love, ys the on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly cauſe, why God oure lovynge father dothe ſo afflicte vs. To what ende then te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dethe he, in this his affliction, &amp; to what purpoſe dothe he ſo often afflicte vs? S. Paul in his fyrſt epiſtell to the Corrinthe ans dothe expreſſe vnto vs the cauſe wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in few wordes, ſaynge, When we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re iudged off the lorde, we are corrected, to thende we ſhoulde not be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned with the worlde. That ys to ſaye, God dothe ſende vs affliction and tribulation, but he dothe not ſende them to diſtroye vs, but rather to chaſtyce vs, to thende ther by we myght amende, &amp; be prouoked to fle vnto hym for mercye and pardon. By
<pb facs="tcp:12546:36"/>we myght not be condemned with the wycked wordlynges.<note place="margin">4. Eſd. 16</note> Eſdras hath the lyke ſaige in his .iiij. boke the. 16. chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. Beholde (ſayethhe) hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger and pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, trouble &amp; anguy the, are ſent as ſcour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, for amendment. Wher vnto ys to be refarred the worthy ſaynge off the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly woman Iudethe.<note place="margin">Iudith. 8.</note> Let vs not ſeke to be avenged (ſayeth ſhe) for the thynge that ys done vnto vs: but conſyder that al the ſe ponyſhentes are farre leſſe then our ſynnes and miſdedes, belevinge alſo that this correction comethe vnto vs, (as to the ſeruates off God) for amendment and not for oure dyſtruction. Now it y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manifeſte, that when we ſuffer any tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bulation, hyt proſede the from God, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that for oure ſalvation. The which thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge when a chriſtean man dothe fayghtful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidere, he ys moved forth with pari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and gladly to be are all his aduerſites in rendrynge harty thankes to God his ſat her for the ſame. And ſo come the it to pas,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> as ſayeth. S. Paul. That tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bryngethe pacience, not off his owne proper nature, but by a more live<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege off the good will off God to wardes vs. And this pacience, brynge the experi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:12546:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>(ſayeth. S. Paul) that vs to ſaye, pacience do the trye and prove oure faygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, yea pacience doth perfytly wytnes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly declare, and ſurely aſſure vs, that the faught off that perſon, that ys paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in his aduerſite, ys no vame, fayned or dead fayght, but fyrme, trew and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velye, in that it indure the the fyre off tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bulation wiih out ether werynes or repy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymge. It ys a common ſaynge amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt vs, that a man dothe not certaynlye knowe his owne ſtomake and boldnes, tyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhuche tyme as he ys retorned from the battayll. For after a man hath felt hym ſelfe ſtout and valiant at the pynche, and wyllinge to do his dewtye to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt off his power, and that not for all the iniures, incomodites, calamites, and miſeryes off the warres, he never founde hym ſelfe dyſcorraged from the fayghtful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erninge of his prince, but hath al wayes paciently and valiantly ſupported all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſardes and troubles, in corragynge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynewallye his companyons, &amp; all wayes ſhowynge a good contynance and luſty cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rage. That men then knowe the how hardey he ys, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he knowethe that he ys in the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber off them that are meite ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours
<pb facs="tcp:12546:37"/>to ſerue the kynge and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men wealthe. And he ys knowen off all his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panyons, yea and off the kynge hym ſelfe. But what thynge hath tryed hym? what thynge hath made hym knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? For ſo the the conſtancye and pacience that he had in aduerſite. For before this pacience, neyther was he knowen to the kynge, ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther yet to his companyons, what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner a man he was, no he was not knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hym ſelfe.<note place="margin">Eccle. 34</note> For as ſayeth the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyke, he that was neuer tempted, what knowethe he? And he that was never pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved, wheroff hathe he experience? Be meanethe that with out eroſſe and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution a man ſhal neuer knowe hym ſelfe certaynlye. The which thynge ys moſt trew. For tyll ſhuche tyme as we haue byn tempted, and tyll ſuche tyme as god hathe layed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs his croſſe that it plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſethe hym to have vs beare. We may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme,<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> or rather preſume off oureſelves, then other wyſſe, as S. Peter, extermed and preſumed off hym ſelfe, when as he ſayed. Thought all men be offended by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe off the, yet will not I be offended, &amp; all thought I ſhould dye with the, yet wil I not denye the, yea I wyll gyve my lyff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12546:37"/>for the. Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Peter vttred theſſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dis, he knewe not very well what he ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, neyther knewe he as yet hym ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And wherfor? By cauſe he had as then neuer byn tempted nor proved. So lyk wyſſe we, yff before we have byn temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or afflicted do vtter the lyke ſaynges, truly, we ſpeake off no cerſayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye for as myche as we never haue byn proved, &amp; ſherfor are all to gyther ignorant off oure ſelves. But when as God oure father, hath ſent vs tribulations and hath gyve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs grace in the ſame to contine we conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and to behaue ourſewes valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, that ys to ſaye, we were neuer dyſcomforted nor aſtoyned nor denyed oure fayght, but haue boldly confeſſed theſame before the face of oure enymes, no thynge extemyng oure lyffes with. S. Paul. But haue wil lyngly dyſpyced and abandoued the ſame for the verytes ſake, accordyng to the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Ieſus Chriſt oure onely maſter, &amp; moſt perfyte exampler. Then are we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, then do we perſayve and knowe by experience that oure fayght ys good &amp; ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vely, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dothe oure<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> companyons knowe vs, and then dothe God hym ſelfe know vs, as he ſayeth to Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Gene. 22.</note> Now I knowe
<pb facs="tcp:12546:38"/>that thow feareſt God, So that there ys no doute but that this probation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience off oure fayght to be good &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>methe off the pacient conſtancye, &amp; conſtant pacience that God hath gyve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, in oure tribulations. For truly the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate and vnbelevers, haue neuer pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience in theyre aduerſites. But they mourmer all wayes agaynſt God &amp; blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme his maieſtye. Which thynge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydere, noved. S. Paul to ſaye, pacien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce bryngethe eyperience (to wytt) experi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence off oure fayght, that ys to ſaye, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience dothe gyve vs experience that oure faight ys good, as a good ſouldioure that hath dilygently done his indevoure in the bataill, conſayveth a certayne and ſure hope, that his prince for whom he hath fought &amp; haſarded his lyffe, wyll gyve hym tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes, reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe hym, &amp; gyve hym prefarme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, charge, and credyte in his real me. Even ſo when as by conſtant paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence oure fayght hath byn proved, and founde good, then dothe oure hope increſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe more then ever it dyd, and do conſeve a fyrine aſſurance, and ſure certitude off oure ſalvation. Then begyne we (as it we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re) partly to knowe and lyvely to feile,
<pb facs="tcp:12546:38"/>that we cannot be damned, but that we ſhall be moſt certaynly ſaved,<note place="margin">Tob. 3.</note> as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the good Tobias, Who ſo ever lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vethe God (ſayeth he) and ſerueth hym a ryght, ys ſure off this, that yff his lyfe be tempted and proved, it ſtandeth in try<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge, and yff he contynewe in pacience, he ſhall haue a rewarde, and be hyghly crowned. To the which agreethe the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly apoſtel. S. Iames, ſaynge,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.</note> Blyſſed ys that man that endure the temptation, for affter that he hath byn proved, he ſhall reſſayve the crowne off lyffe, that God hath promyſed to thoſſe that love hym.</p>
            <p>And this ys it, that the apoſtell teacethe vs, when as he ſayethe, probation,<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that ys to ſaye, the experience that throught pacience we haue off oure ſtronge and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinſyble fayght, workethe (or rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendrythe) hope. But vpon what thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ys this oure hope founded and bylded? Yff it were founded and ſtayed vpon the force &amp; worthynes off oure pacience, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould it haue, but a ſlender fondation, myche lyke vnto that edifice that ys byl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the ſande, But wher vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ys it ſituatede? vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the onely certayntey off the verytable promyſſes off the lorde,
<pb facs="tcp:12546:39"/>who ſayeth in. S. Matthew. Blyſſed a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re all thoſſe that ſuffer perſecution for ryghtouſnes ſake,<note place="margin">Math. 10</note> for theyrs ys the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome off heaven, and agayne he ſayethe. He that wyll go about to ſave his ſowll, that ys to ſaye, his carnall and temporal lyffe, he ſhall loſſe theſame, but he that ſhall loſſe his fowll, that ys to ſaye, he that ſhall wyllyngly abandon his lyffe for my ſake &amp; for the goſples, he ſhal ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſave it. Vpon theſſe promyſſes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lyke, which are infinite in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ys oure hope all wayes founded &amp; bylded, as the only foundation theroff. And not vpon oure owne workes, pacien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce or worthynes. And this hope, ys not confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ſayeth ſaynt Paul, that ys to ſaye, that all thoſſe that do fyrmely hope after the thynges that God hath promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, they ſhall never be dyſſayved not fruſtrated off theyre expectation and attente: They ſhall neuer be confounded befor the vngodly &amp; vnbeleuers theyre eny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: It ſhall never repent them, neyther ſhall they be aſſhamed for that they haue beleved in the promiſſes off God. For aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuredly they ſhall haue, that they haue hoped for, namly that which God hath
<pb facs="tcp:12546:39"/>promyſed them. And on the other ſyde, the vnbelevers and vngodly ſhall haue no ocaſion, to laffe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſkorne. For out off all dout they ſhall be ſaved, as teſtifiethe the prophet Eſaias.<note place="margin">Eſai. 28.</note> Whoſoeuer beleve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the in hym, ſhall not be confounded. Alſo it ys written in the pſalmes. Blyſſed ys the man that hopethe in the lorde,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> ffor God ſavethe thoſſe that truſiethe in him. But what nede I here to allege the ſayin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges off theſſe .ij. prophetes, Dauid, &amp; Eſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ias, ſeyng that all the ſcriptures tendy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the to none other ende, and al moſt reace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the noneother doctrine, but onely that all thoſſe that vnfaynedly do repoſſe theyre confidence in God, ſhalbe delyvered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all theyre tribulations, and ſhalbe ſaved trought the grace and mercye off the lorde Ieſus Chriſt. And there for gyve eare vnto the lyvely and puyſance conſolation, that the apoſiell dothe gyve vnto vs in his epeſtell to the Ebrieus, &amp; els where,<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.</note> ſayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge. Wherfor let vs alſo (for as myche as we are compaſſed about with ſo great a multitude of witneſſes) that ys to ſaye, ſo great a nomber off them that are gone before vs. Laye a waye all that preſſeth downe, and the ſynne that hangethe ſo
<pb facs="tcp:12546:40"/>faſt on, let vs ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne with pacience vnto the battaylle that ys ſet before vs, lokynge vn to Ieſus the captayne and fynyſher off ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re fayght, which for the ioye that was ſet before hym, a bode the croſſe, and dyſſpy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced the ſhame, and ys now ſet downe on the ryght hande off the throne off God, Conſyder therfor and conſyder agayne, how he indured ſuche contradiction off ſynners, leſte ye ſhould be weryed &amp; faynt in your myndes, for ye haue not yet reſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto bloud, ſtryvynge agaynſt ſynne, and haue forgotten the exhortation that ſpeaketh vnto you as vnto childerin. My ſonne diſpyſe not thow the chaſtenynge of the lorde, neyther faynte when thow art rebuked off hym, for whom the lorde lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vethe, hym he chaſtynethe, yea, he ſkor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gethe euery ſonne that he reſayvethe, yff ye indure chaſtenynge God offrethe hym ſelfe vnto you, as vnto ſonnes. What ſonne ys he whom the father chaſtynethe not? Yff ye be not vnder correction (wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>off all are pertakers) then are ye baſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and not ſonnes. Therfor ſeynge we haue had fathers off oure owne fleſhe, which corrected vs, and we gave them re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerence, ſhall we not myche rather be in
<pb facs="tcp:12546:40"/>ſubiection vnto the father off ſpirites and lyffe? And they verely, for a fewe dayes nortered vs after they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e owne pleaſure, but he norterethe vs for oure profyte, to thende that he may miniſter off his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto vs. No manner chaſtenynge for the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tyme ſemethe to be ioyous, but grevous, never the leſſe after warde it bryngethe the quyete frute off ryghtouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vnto them that are excercyſed there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by. For thought oure outwarde man pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſhe, yet the inward man ys renewed day by day, for oure tribulation,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4</note> which ys momentany and lyght, preparethe an excedyng and an eternall wayght off glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye vnto vs, whylles we loke not on the thynges that are ſene, but on the thynges which are not ſene. For the thynges which are ſene are temporall, but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which are not ſene, are eternall. For we knowe, that yf the earthly manſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this body were dyſtroyed,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> we haue a byl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dige of god, an habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not made with handes but eternall in heauen. My fryndes and brytherin, theſſe worthy ſayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges are written for oure doctryne, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that we throught pacience and conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off the ſcriptures myght haue hope.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb facs="tcp:12546:41"/>your ſelves then, in theſſe wordes, haue pacience, be thankfull all wayes vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to oure particuler and generall father.</p>
            <p>Yff at any tyme it pleaſethe hym to make you pertakers off the healtfull ſuffryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, of Ieſus Chriſt his onely ſonne, and off all the fayghtfull chriſteans that here to fore haue ſuffred ffor his name ſake.</p>
            <p>Haue a ſure hope, that yff you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer wiſh the ſonne off God, ye ſhall alſo raigne with hym. And yff ye do comu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicate with him, paciently berynge his croſſe in this worlde, be cauſe you wolde be founde obedient vnto the good wyll off God his father, ye ſhall alſo be made ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto hym, lyvyng &amp; raignyng in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in immortalite moſt happye. And all wayes remember and fayghtfully con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyder this one thynge, wheroff the holy goſt by the pen off ſaynt Paul dothe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyſhe vs, ſaynge, The afflictions off this worlde, are not worthy off the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to come, the which ſhalbe reueled on vs. In this firme confidence, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myte your ſelues holy, to the more then father<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly prouidence off our God. And ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym with a good wyll and erneſt myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de with out all diſſimulation. Our ffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy wyll be done. And then ſaye al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo.
<pb facs="tcp:12546:41"/>With a ſure confidence, as ſayeth.<note place="margin">Hebr 13. Pſal. 55. Pſal. 117.</note> S. Paul. The lorde ys my helper. I wyll fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re no thynge that man can do vnto me. Fere not that God wyll forſake you, in what ſo ever miſerable ſtate it pleaſethe hym to brynge you. For he hath ſayd,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 1.</note> I wyll not forſake the, nor abandone the. Ye wolde not relynquyſhe, not forſake a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath ſuffred any thynge for you. And do ye thynke then, that god who one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ys good, wyll forſake vs, who onely haue ſuffred for his name ſake? O fryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des let it neuer enter into your hartes, for it ys not poſſible aſſure your ſelves.</p>
            <p>And forther more, be aſcartayned that no thynge ſhall happen vnto you, but that which God hath eternally ordayned for you. And all thought all the tyrantes off the worlde, and the wholl worlde it ſelfe, ſhould conſpyre agaynſt you, they are not to be feared. For you can drynke no thi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge els, but that cuppe that God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared for you, from the begynnynge. Ye can ſuffer no more, nor non other wyſſe, nor at non other tyme, then God hathe ordayned. Do not ye knowe, that the kynde off deathe off the ſonne off God, was before determyned? It behoved hym
<pb facs="tcp:12546:42"/>to be exalted, as he hym ſelfe teſcifie the in S. Iohn, that ys to ſaye, it behoved hym to be ceucifyed,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.</note> he coulde not dye off any other deathe. And the tyme alſo wherin it be hoved hym to dye, was it not certayn lye ordayned and apoynied? Yeas truly, as witneſſe the Daniel in his. <hi>9.</hi> chapter.</p>
            <p>How often tymes hane ye read, in the hiſtorye of the lyffe off Ieſy Chriſte, that his ennymes ſought dyuers meanes to ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke hym, and yet they could not, by cauſe that his howre was not come? that ys to ſaye,<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.</note> that the tyme was not them come, that God his father had determined that he ſhould be taken. But when his hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re was come, they toke hym at theire plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, trought the ineuitable ordinance off God, who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd delyuer hym into they<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re handes, and gaue them power ouer hym, as he ſayed to Pilate. Thow ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt haue no manner off power ouer me, yff it were not gyven vnto the, from a houe. Lykwyſſe he ſayed vnto the Iewes, Ye are come forthe as it were agaynſt a theaffe, with ſwordes &amp; ſtaues for to ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke me. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was daiely with rou in the temple, ye ſireched forthe no handes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt me,<note place="margin">Luc. 22.</note> but (ſayeth he in. S. Luke)
<pb facs="tcp:12546:42"/>This ys eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> youre very houre, &amp; the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er off darcknes. The place lykwyſſe wheras he ſhould ſuffer, was it not alſo determyned? Be hym ſelfe declareth vnto vs, that yeas. For he ſayeth, It ys not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the prophet, that ys to ſaye, the Aleſſias, or the annoynted of god, ſhould pery ſhe, but at Ieruſalem. And of thoſſe that ſhould comdemne hym,<note place="margin">Math. 20</note> &amp; put hym to deathe, was there no thynge determined in the ſecret counſayll off he deite? What ſhould we doute theroff, for he hym ſelf ſayed, Beholde, we go vp to Ieruſalem, and the ſonne off man ſhall be delyuered into the handes off the hyghe preiſtes and ſcrybes, and they ſhall comdemue him to deathe, and ſhall delyuer hym to the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylles to be mocked, and to be ſcourged, &amp; to be crucifyed, &amp; the thyrde daye he ſhal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſſe agayne. And off hym that dyd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traye hym, what? was there no thynge determined before?<note place="margin">Math. 26</note> Barke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what he hym ſelfe ſayethe, Verely, I ſaye vnto you, that one off you ſhall betraye me &amp;c. The ſonne off man goethe as it ys wrytten off hym, but wo vnto that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ys betrayed, It had hyn good for that man, yff he had not hyn borne. Then
<pb facs="tcp:12546:43"/>Iudas, which betrayed hym, ſayed maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, ys it I? Ieſus ſayd vnto hym, thow haſt ſayde, that ys to ſaye, thow haſt ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed the truthe, it ys even thow, that was ordayned for thit purpoſe from the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge. This maye ye ſe, how all thynges conſernyng Ieſus Chriſt was gyded by the prouidence and determination of god his father. Truly there happyned no thynge vnto hym, that was not certainlye ordayned and appoynted before. Wherby we may eaſely gather, that no thyng ſhal happen vnto vs his members, that God hath not ordained for vs, thought all the men off the worlde wolde conſpyre to gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and with them all the develes in hel, or in the eayre, with all theyre iniquite craſtes, treaſons, wyckednes, thretenyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, ſtrenght and condemnations, yet ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they not abrydge oure courſe, not prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge oure lyffe, one moment. How great then ys oure puſillanimite &amp; weaknes? When as al thynges dependynge enterely vpon the only prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, in whoſſe ſure ſafgard and protection. we are and haue our beynge, and yet for all that we fere a mortall man, and that more ys, a weake woman, that to daye ys greue as
<pb facs="tcp:12546:43"/>the greſſe, and to morowe ſhalbe caſt into the fornace. Continewally (as ſayeth the prophet Eſaias) we ſtande in fere, off the furye off them that trouble vs, and in the meane tyme do forget the lorde that hathe created vs, that hathe ſiret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ont the heavens, and hath layde the fondations of the earthe. O that we are people off lytell fayght. But ſome man paraduenture wyll replye and ſaye vnto me. We are not Ieſus Chriſte, therfor it ys not certayne whether god hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the thynge that happyneth vnto vs, as he dyd vnto Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; whether he hath charge and care ouer vs, as he had ouer Ieſus Chriſte? wherfor not with out a cauſe we do fere the imaginations and entrepryſes off oure enymes, agaynſt vs. O ſaynge all to gyther myred with infidelite, this ys that I ſpacke off before, alas, we haue no fayght, for wherin can we more ſhowe oure incredulite, then ſo to reſtrayne the eternal prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, as to tende no forther then ouer the only perſon off Ieſus Chriſte? So ſhould god be the God off Ieſus Chriſte only, &amp; not oure God alſo? Wherfor then do we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in hym? Wherfor then do we repoſſe
<pb facs="tcp:12546:44"/>oure wholl truſt and confidence only in hym? Wherfor then do we call hym, ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re God, oure father, &amp; oure ſavioure? yff the prouidence off God do not tende ouer vs alſo, and yff he haue no ſolicitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and care ouer vs, then hathe the ſpiret off god abuſed vs with a notable lye, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as by the penn off.<note place="margin">1. pet. 5.</note> S. Peter he ſayed, Laſte all your care vpon God, for he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethe for you. But truly the lorde myght iuſtly ſaye off vs now, that which ſome tyme he ſpake off Ephraim in the. 11. chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter off the prophet Oreas,<note place="margin">Oze. 11.</note> I bare Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im in myn armes as he that noryſhe the them, &amp; yet they woulde not knowe that I had care off them. O to myche ingra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude? O infidelite incomparable? Tell me I praye you, are not tow ſparrowes off les walewe with God, then we are? Truly God hathe not ſo myche extemed them,<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> for he dyed not for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as he hath done for vs, and yet Ieſus Chriſt teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto vs, that a ſparowe ſhall not fall vpon the grounde, without the wyll off oure heauenly father.<note place="margin">Luc. 12.</note> And what then? Shall we fall without his prouidence &amp; determinate decre? No truly. Do we not knowe that euen the heares off oure hed
<pb facs="tcp:12546:44"/>are all nombred? Do we not knowe that god hath diſpoſed all thynges by nomber, wayght, and meaſure? Are we ignorant off this, that all thynges haue theyre ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted tyme? and that all thynge that ys vnder the heavens paſſethe by his cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe? as ſayeth the Lceleſiaſtike. Do we not knowe that God hath gyven to man, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and nomber off dayes? Haue we not ſene wrytten that there ys a tyme off byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.<note place="margin">Eccle. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and a tyme off deathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Haue we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, or rather do we not vnderſtande, that which ys wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the boke off Iob, &amp; that we heare ſo often ſonge in the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che.<note place="margin">Iob. 14.</note> The dayes off man ſurely are deter mined, the nomber off his monthes are onely knowen vnto the, thow haſt appoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hym his bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, which he cannot go beyounde. What ys that to ſaye, God hath appo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ynted bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and limytes vnto the lyffe off man? It ys to ſaye, that God hath ordayned euery man a certayne ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to lyve, the which tyme we cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer pas nor go beyonde. But this ys not all. For it behovethe vs alſo to tarry the appoynted tyme and as it were to touche the limited boundes. Wherfor yff we wil directly vnderſtand this place off Iob, we
<pb facs="tcp:12546:45"/>muſt dyligently conſyder what ys to ſaye a bounde or a lymite. Truly when a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce off grounde ys lymited and bounded, it dothe not only ſignifye that it goethe no farther, but alſo that it tendethe and ſire chethe to the bounde. Wherfor it ys not inought to conſyder that we ſhal not pas the tyme that God hathe lymited, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyned vs to lyve, but alſo we muſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuredli perſwade oureſelves that we ſhal lyve as lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge as he hath ordayned vs to ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve. And truly ſo ſhall we do in the diſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te off all oure enymes, all thought they wolde ſwelt theyre hartes. And tell me forther more, haue men gyuen vs oure lyffe? No forſothe. No more can they ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it awaye from vs. God, with out a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny other hath gyven it vs, and God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dothe take it awaye. For he ys the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de off deathe, as well as off lyffe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the appoynted tyme off oure dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ys come, let vs aſſure oureſelfes that it ys god only, and none other that dothe kyll vs. For he ſayeth. It ys I that kyll, and make a lyve agayne. And therfor when it ſhall pleaſe hym to kyll vs, that ys to ſaye, to take awaye this miſerable lyffe off the fleſſe: let vs ſaye with Iob.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12546:45"/>
            <p>The lorde hath gyven, and the lorde hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it awaye, blyſſed be the name off the lorde. Let vs conſyder, and folowe the example off Iſaac, who ſo paciently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted hym ſelfe to be bonde off his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, beynge redye to put hym to deathe. Oeſyrynge the infinite bounte off oure God, ſo to bynde oure members and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, that there appere in vs no man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of thynge, that may reſiſte, gainſaye or replye in any reſpect againſt his good wyll and pleaſure. But before all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge let vs folowe the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Ieſus Chriſt oure only ſavioure and maſter, who ſeyin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge his deathe approchynge ſayed to god his father, My father, not as I wyll, but as thou wyllt, thy wyll be done and not my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne. Let vs then offer vnto God the father, oureſelfes for a ſacrefyce, whoſe ſavoure all thought it be evell and ſtynkyng in the noſe off the worlde, yet it ys good &amp; agrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble vnto God by Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom, that ys to ſaye, in the fayght and confidence off whom, we do dedycat. and offer oure ſelves, when we perſayve oure houre to approche. And in the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne tyme let vs not tempt God, let vs not ſerche out, &amp; prouoke oure enymes, that
<pb facs="tcp:12546:46"/>ys to ſaye, thoſſe that with out a cauſe wolde vs evell, but rather in folowynge the example off Chriſt and his apoſtles, let vs with drawe oure ſelfes thither, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as it ſhall pleaſe the prouydence off oure God and father to addreſſe vs. And what ſo euer betyde, let vs not fere me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no, let vs not fere them, for God dothe inhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and for byd vs theſame, ſayinge by his prophet,<note place="margin">Eſai. 41.</note>, Fere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, for I am with you. And ſeynge that god dothe forbynd vs to fere men, can we fere them with out ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne? No truly. But to what purpoſe do we fere them? Men off them ſelues are no thynge: Men off them ſelues can do no thynge: and yff at onye tyme they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue any power, the ſame power come the onely vnto them from God, and ys gyve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto them onely to accomplyſhe &amp; execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te the wyll off God. Wherfor they can not at any tyme, do any thynge but that, that God wyll haue done, by theyre mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration. Wherfor then do we fere them? Geying we are onely vnder the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tection and ſafgard off God, who ys all myghty. Tell me I pray you, yff we had an enyme in Ingland, &amp; the Quiene, who ys but a woman had promyſed vs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect
<pb facs="tcp:12546:46"/>and defende vs agaynſt oure enyme, would we then fere hym? I ſuppoſe, no. And yet we are not aſhamed to fere oure enymes,<note place="margin">Gene. 15.</note> after that God who only ys all myghty, and off power to preſerue, hath ſayed vnto euery one off vs, Fere not, for I am thy protector, thy defence, and thy reward ſhalbe excedynge great. Yff after this certayne promys and diuers other lyke, we do yet fere men, oure enymes, It muſt off neceſſite followe that we do doute off the power, goodnes, &amp; allmygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty helpe off God. Ys this the honour that we beare vnto his diuine maieſtye? Can we do hym a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er iuiure, then not to credyte and obaye his worde? Why rather do we not ſaye with he prophet Dauid, and that with vnfayned lyppes voyde off all Ipocryſie. My hope and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence ys onely in the lorde God, I fere not what man can do vnto me? Why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould we fere the deathe, which theſſe wordly wyſſe men (and yet in very dede folles) do make appere vnto vs ſo horry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and expouentable. For truly that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that now fere the deathe, doth great iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vnto Ieſus Chriſte which hath ouer come theſame. And ſemethe, that he do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the
<pb facs="tcp:12546:47"/>dyſpayre off eternall lyffe, that Ieſus Chriſt, by his deathe hath purchaſed for vs. But peraduenture ye wyll ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me, that Ieſus Chriſt hym ſelfe in the tyme off his croſſe, dyd fere deathe, and therfor it ys no marvayl, thought we do fere it, in whom there ys no ſhuche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and conſtancye? Truly the fleſhe dothe alwayes abuſe hyr ſelfe with the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple off Ieſus Chriſte, ſhe dothe abuſe it, for ſhe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not rightfully vſe it, in as my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as the fleſhe ys all wayes repongnant vnto the ſpiret and the good wyll off god. And for as miche as you wil heri followe the example off Ieſus Chriſt, well I am contented, fere deathe: But fere it, as Ieſus Chriſt dyd fere it. Yff you wyll ſaye, that Ieſus Chriſt had fere off dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, conſyder the ſame alſo to be on ſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſorte, as the fere theroff dyd not ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe hym backe from the voluntarye obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence off God his father, and from ſaying with vnfained lyppes, My father thy wil be done: nor (his howre beynge come) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the offrynge of hym ſelfe wyllyngly into the handes off his enymes, to be crucified and put to deathe. So thow ſo (o thow
<pb facs="tcp:12546:47"/>fleſhe) for yff thow do otherwyſſe, then doſt thow not followe the example off Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte in ferynge deathe, but thow woldeſt couer thy puſyllanimyte and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections with the example off the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne off God, in whoſſe lyffe was neuer founde any imperfection. Ye wyll an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me, and ſaye, we fere not deathe, for any fere we haue to be damned, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for any diffidence that we haue off eternall lyffe: But do beleve and are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynlye aſſured, that oure God, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only we haue oure confidence, wyll not damne vs, but off his mercye, wyll gyue vnto vs eternall lyffe for the ryghtouſnes and merytes ſake off his ſonne oure ſavi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oure Ieſus Chriſte: But we fere the dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the for the humayne vnderſtandyng that we haue, of the great payne that ſome do ſuffer in deyinge, and eſpecially, in deying by fyre, for we ſuppoſe that payne to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount all pacience. O fonde fleſhe, thy voyce ys all wayes full off the love off thy ſelfe, and off a ſecret diffidence and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt off the all myghty power, wyſdome and goodnes off the lydynge God. I am ſure, thow doſt not comprehende it, nor vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de it, neyther thow wylte not, nor
<pb facs="tcp:12546:48"/>canneſt not. And therfor I wyll no more indevoure my ſelfe to ſpeke vnto the, for it were but loſte laboure. But I wyll derecte my wordes, vnto all the childerin of God, who (as. S. Paul ſayeth) are led with the ſpiret off God,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> &amp; them wyll I now arme agaynſt all the difficultes, that this curſed fleſhe had wonte to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte, when as it behoued vs to beare the croſſe off Chriſte for the glorye off God.<note place="margin">Te great no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber off mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera that lat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly haue byn borne in In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland do teſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifye the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rarye.</note> And namly agaynſt that, which ſhe latly obiected ſaynge, that the payne that a 01 chriſtean dothe ſuffer by deyeyng in the fyre, dothe ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t all pacience. O ſeyinge ſayinge, O ſhamfull blaſphemye, that aparently denyethe the infinite pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, and the incomparable bountye of god, O ye chriſteans? Wyll ye gyve credence vnto this abominable and wycked fleſhe, which ſekethe no thynge els but to pull vs from the croſſe off Chriſt: and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently from oure ſalvation, vnto the which it pleaſeth oure father ſo benyngly to call vs? O how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you abyde to heare this with pacience? For yff it be not poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyble for a chriſtean man paciently and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly to ſuffer the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t off fyre, as this wycked fleſhe (all wayed rebellynge
<pb facs="tcp:12546:48"/>agaynſt god) woloe perſwade ver I praye you tell me then. What meanethe Ieſus Chriſt by this ſayinge which he teaceth his diſſiples,<note place="margin">Mar. 9.</note> That there ys no thynge im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſſible to hym that beleuethe? Wherfor yff all thynges are poſſible to the belever, (as ſayeth the veryte) then ys it poſſyble for a man that beleveth paciently to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer deathe, and that by fyre. Wherby it ys apparant that the torment off fyre do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the not ſurmounte all pacience. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more, what meanethe. S. Paul,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he affirmethe that god ys fayghtful, &amp; wil not ſuffer vs to be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted a bove ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re powers, but ſhal in the middes of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation make a waye, that we ſhalbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beare it? Dothe this texte offer vnto vs, that the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of fyre dothe ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the pacience off a chriſtean? No truly, but rather the contrarye. Forther more the ſcriptures do witneſſe,<note place="margin">Eſai. 53. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>br. 4.</note> that the ſonne of God ys ſhuche a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as was ful of ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, and as hathe good experience off infir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mites. For in that he ſuffred and was te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, he ys off power to helpe thoſſe that are tempted. For we haue not an hyghe preſte, which cannot haue compaſſion off oure infirmites. Wherfor then, yf the
<pb facs="tcp:12546:49"/>ſonne off God, in whom we do beleve, &amp; for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we do ſuffer afflictions, haue experime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in hym ſelfe, oure ſorowes, &amp; not only ys able to helpe vs, but alſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>freth with vs, as the hed with the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ys there any payne now that we are not able to bere with all pacient conſtancye, and conſtant pacience? For yff we ſhould fere that God wolde forſake vs, when as for his holy name, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do throwe vs into the fyre, what aſſurance then can we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue that God wyll gyve vs eternall lyffe? How dare we then boſt oure ſelves, that we are certayne, and voyde off all doute, off our ſalvation? Can we offer agreater iniure to God, then to fere that he wyll forſake vs when as we ſuffer for the teſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monye off his truthe? No truly. For a man, that ys evell off nature, wyll not abandon a nother man that ſuffreth ony thynge for his ſake, (as I haue ſayd befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re) how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it then enter into the thought off a chriſtean, that God (who only ys good), will forſake hym, when he ys tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mented for his worde?<note place="margin">Sapi. 1.</note> Were this a good opinion off the lorde as the holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re commandethe vs to haue? No truly. Even ſo neuer entred it into the harte off
<pb facs="tcp:12546:49"/>a fayghtfull man. But what (a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt other thynges) ought a chriſtean man to thynke, when he comethe to the fyre to be borned? He ought truly to remember that which ys writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the .xvi. chapter off the boke off wyſdome, wher as we re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de this ſaynge, The fyre forgate his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſtrenght by cauſe the ryghtous myght be noryſhed, for thy creature that ſerue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the the (which art the maker) ys feirſe in ponyſhynge the vnryghtous, but doth aſſwage it ſelfe, and ys eaſye and gentyl to do good vnto ſhuche as put theyre truſte in the. Theſſe wordes do not declare that the torment of fyre ys an intollerable pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne vnto a chriſtean, but contrary wyſſe, that the payne ys lyght and eaſye to beare for as myche as by the power off the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fydence that we haue in God the lorde creator off all thynges, the vyolence off the fyre ys ſo tempered and aſſwaged vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that wheras the vnbeleuers do burſt out by impacience, and mourmer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt God, we do ſuffer paciently and wyllynglye in gyvynge prayſes vnto the lorde in the myddes off all oure extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</p>
            <p>In folowynge therin the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample off the thre younge me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who beyn
<pb facs="tcp:12546:50"/>bounde in the myddes off a flambynge fornes, dyd ſanctifie and prayffe the forde God, who performed and accomplyſhed then vnto them, that which he before pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſed by the mouthe of his holy prophet, ſayinge, yff thow walkeſie thorowe the fyre,<note place="margin">Eſai. 43.</note> it ſhall not borne the, and the flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſhall not kendyll vpon the, for I am the lorde thy God, the holy one off Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, thy Savioure. Ys there now any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant reaſon or cauſe, why a chriſtean, who only hathe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in God by Ieſus Chriſte, ſhoulde fere the fyrye fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, wherwith men do threaten them?</p>
            <p>The fyre ys not noyful. vnto a chriſtean man, but very profytable, for as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſethe the ſcripture,<note place="margin">Sapi. 3. Pro. 11.17 Pſal. 65. 1. per. 1.</note> It workethe the lyke effecte in a chriſtean, that it dothe in gold or ſyluer, that ys to ſaye, It doth proue hym, it doth purifie &amp; pourge hym, with ont conſumynge. And truly is waye the thinge dyrectlye, a chriſtea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en into the fyre, maye worthely he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto the fyrye buſhe that Aloyſes ſawe in the mount Dreb,<note place="margin">Exod. 3.</note> which buſhe for all that it was on a flambye fyre yet dyd it not conſume. Be may alſo be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto the chinyng worme, that beyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:12546:50"/>in the fyre, dothe not peryſhe, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, but contrarywyſſe ys therby pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from fylth, &amp; made more bewtyfull then yff it were waſhed with all the wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter off the worlde. Wherfor let vs then aſſure oure ſelves, and from hens forthe let vs neuer fere the fyre that ſo ſone va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>het awaye, for I am ſure that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue paſſed through the fyre, we ſhall ſaye with Ieſus the ſoune off Syrache, I was not bornte, no, not in the myddes off the fyre. Let vs not fere men, that worke no thynge els vniuerſallye, but va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite. Let vs not alſo fere deathe, for to fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re deathe (as ſayeth a certayne wyſſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) ys no thynge els, but to ſeme to be wyſſe, and yet in very dede to be no thynge leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. Fynally let vs not ſtande in fere off any manner off crcatures. Let vs fere God only, let vs gyve ouer oure ſelues vnto hym, and abyde vnder his protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that done, let vs not care for, nor paſſe off any thynge, for ſo the ſpiryte off goo admoni heth vs by. S. Paul ſaying,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> I wyll that you be with ont all ſolicitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. And agayne, care not for any thynge. And by the mouthe off S. Peter,<note place="margin">1. pet. 5.</note> he ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth, Laſt your care vpon God, for he ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rethe
<pb facs="tcp:12546:51"/>for you. But peraduenture you wyll obiecie agaynſt me. How dare you now go a bout to perſwade vs, that we ſhoulde not care? Was there euer in all oure lyffes a greater occaſion off care mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there ys at this preſent. Who dothe not ſe how ſome are exiled out off theyre natyve coutrye, compaſſed a bout with miſerye, pouertye and ſondrye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, voyde off all conforte and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation: on the other ſyde ſome impreſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſhut vp from all fryndes, acquayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and kyndred, abydyng every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſentence off comdemnation, to be gyven over into the handes off the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men to be executed. Some other haue loſt all theyre goodes and landes theyre howſes ſealed vp, theyre wyffes &amp; chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren lyinge vpon theyre handes voyde off all releffe and forſaken off the worlde, bey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge be come an obloque and a laffyngſtoc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke vnto al people, and as it were poynted at with the fynger. And yet you ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs, that we ſhould not care for any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge. Ys it now tyme to ſaye, care not at all? Truly my fryndes I haue in very dede ſo ſayed vnto you, &amp; do ſo ſaye agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, for as myche as God, who ys your
<pb facs="tcp:12546:51"/>God, &amp; wyll ſhowe hym ſelfe to be your God, hath commanded you to do ſo, for he ſayeth playnly, Lare not for any thynge. Lan ye now then take care for any off your affayres, be they never ſo great with ont offendynge and dyſſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge off your God and father? It ys not poſſible. Wherfore I woulde conſayll you to depend wholy vpon hym. Who hath ſayde, Caſt your care vpon the lorde, and he wyll helpe in the tyme off nede. And on the other ſyde all thought you myght iuſtly be carefull for your affayres with out offence, tell me yff it pleaſe you, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ſeruethe all your care? What comodyte doth hit brynge Truly none at al. Knowe ye not that of many cares &amp; great thought taking, there comethe no thynge but dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes? Galomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in the ſprirete in the v. chapter of the Eccleſiaſtic. dothe playn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly teſtifie the ſame vnto vs, Lykwyſſe yff we had dylygently ingrauen that diuine and frutfull leſſou that the ſoune of God dothe leue vnto vs in the ende off the .vi. chapter off. S. Matthew, ye ſhould wel perſayue that all oure care and thought takynge cannot in ony reſpect further the leſt byſoues that we haue. Wyll you the
<pb facs="tcp:12546:52"/>for no thynge dyſquyete your ſelfes &amp; bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke your hede, and in ſo doyinge offende youre father, in que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhynge therby his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therly prouidence and great care that he hath ouer you? Ye allege that ye are out off your natyve contrye, who ſeeth not how vayne this your allegation ye. Yff ye thought your ſelfes rahter the childrin off God, then the ſonnes off mortall men after the freſhe, ye woulde conſyder that where ſo euer you become vpon the face off the earthe that you are in the contrye and kyngdom off your father, for dothe not the ſcripture playnely teache vs, that the earthe ys the lordes &amp;c. Which thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, yff it be trew, as there ys no thynge more certayne, then are we not out off oure owne contrye wher ſo euer we beco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, for that land or contrye wherin we dwell, ys oure fathers, by creation, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion and gyfte, and it ys oures by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys gyven vnto vs his childerin. Are not theſſe ſayinges then the bloſſomes off incredulite? Yes truly, for yff we dyd not more ſavor of the fleſhe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſpiret, yf we were not more worldly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly they ſhould new<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proced out of oure mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. Forther more yf oure love were but
<pb facs="tcp:12546:52"/>as perfitly fixed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſpouſe Ieſꝯ, as the love of a faightful wyffe ys vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, we woulde be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for his ſake to abandon all, &amp; go where as he ys. For what fayghtfull honeſt woman ys there, that havynge hyr huſband in a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trye, &amp; ſendynge for hyr, dothe not furth with forſake father-and mother, frynde and acquayntance, goodes and landes, no thynge regardyng neyther peryll, nor pouertye that may happen vnto hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo that ſhe may be in the folowſhype and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye off hyr huſbande. And wherfor?</p>
            <p>By cauſe ſhe louethe hym, and hath hyr confidence and truſt in hym, and ys ſure that ſhe ſhal participate with hym, what ſo euer he hathe. And ought not we chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teans, (vnles we wolde be reputed vnna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turall branches, vnkynde lovers, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent perſons) to abando<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and forſake for the loue off oure heavenly ſpouſe Ieſus Chriſt, (who hathe maryed vs vnto him ſelfe with the rynge off fayght) all word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; fleſhlye pleaſure, what, and howe manye ſo ouer they be, yea and oure lyves to. As dyvers vertious wymen ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue done in tyme paſte as the hiſtories teſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye, for the love off theyr huſbandes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12546:53"/>
            <p>Wherfor now yff your celeſtiall huſbond Ieſus Thriſte for your ſalvation and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modite, and be cauſe he woulde make, you lyke vnto hym ſelfe, dothe now call you out off your owne contrye, do ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſſe to folowe him, which ys the author of lyffe, the preſeruer from perylles, the gyver off all good gyfftes, and the moſt fayghtfull louer off oure ſoules, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as a weake woman wold not refuſſe to followe hyr vukynde huſbande who ys no thynge els but earthe aſſhes, fleſhe, blond and corruption, hauynge no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayntie off his lyffe, nor no full aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of his perſon nor preſence. O to mychs ingratitude, O loue imperfete, or rather vtterly que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched, or els beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge lovers, the very enymes off thy lovyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ſpowſe. Can there be a greater iniure then this. No truly. But ye wyll an ſwer me and ſaye, It were but a ſmall matter to be out off oure contrye, yff we had any certayne dwellynge place wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto we myght repayre, but we knowe not where to be come, nor whyther to go. We neuer traueled ſo farre, and the contrye &amp; people ys vtterly vnknowen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs? My fryndes let it ſuffice that god
<pb facs="tcp:12546:53"/>of his goodnes hath hytherto gyven you howſſes to dwell in, for in that reſpect truly he hath done more for you then he dyd for his owne naturall ſonne, who ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer had any. The foxes (ſayeth he) hath holes,<note place="margin">Math. 8. Luc 9.</note> and the byrdes off the eayre haue neſtes, but the ſonne aff man hath not wheron to reſt his hedd. Do you not ſe how that the ſonne off God hym ſelfe had no earthly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion nor dwellynge pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce off his owne, and yet not with ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge he dyd not complayne off any thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, he dyd not dyſcomfort hym ſelfe. Ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther yet was he at any tyme deſtitute off lodgynge, for his father in whom he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly truſted dyd prouyde for hym, wherfor, yff that you now beyinge in ſtrange con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes are with out habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off your ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, reioyſſe therin, for in that reſpect you are confyrmable and lyke vnto the ſonne off God. Behaue your ſelfe in this eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, as you knowe he dyd gouerne hym ſelfe, and it ſhall happen vnto you, as it dyd vnto hym, that ys to ſaye, Content your ſelues with thynges preſent, truſt in God, and he wyll never leve you, nor forſake you. Ieſus Chriſt alſo your celeſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all huſband wyll neuer forſake you, dyd
<pb facs="tcp:12546:54"/>ye euer kno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>we any good huſbande, that in lyme off nede dyd abandon his eſpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wyffe. in ſuffeinge hyr to range at ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ote with out hauynge any reſpect vnto hyr. Ieſus Chriſte ys that only good huſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bande, for he hath gyden his lyffe for his wyffe. Were it poſſyble, now, that he woulde forſake hyr in levynge hyr deſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te off healpe? In myn opinion, it were not poſſyble, his infinite gooddes coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de not ſuffer it. Wherfor no doute he wyll prouyde lodgynge for you, aſſure your ſelves off that: and trulye it ys an eaſye thynge, for hym to do it, for all the howſes and dwellynges off the worlde are his, as wytneſſet he the prophet Dauid, who ſayethe, The earthe and all the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytude theroff ys the lordes. For it ys with God, as with a huſbande that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the diuers manſion places, the which al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo by the common ryght off mariage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe vnto his wyffe, who cauſethe his wyffe to dwel in which howſe it pleaſeth hym, and when he lyſte he cauſethe hyr to remove and to change habitation as he thynketh beſt, and al wayes the wyffe vs contented, beying an honeſt woman &amp; belytynge in the company of hyr huſban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de.
<pb facs="tcp:12546:54"/>Then ſo, Ieſus Chriſte, who ys the lorde off the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uerſall worlde, who alſo by fayght hathe eſpouſed you,<note place="margin">Ole. 2.</note> wyll haue this prerogaty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe alſo, na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to place you in which of his howſes it pleaſethe hym beſte: your parte ys to obaye, &amp; wyllyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly to dwell in that place where he wyll haue you. And there to remayne, in lea dynge a chriſtean lyffe, tyll ſhuche tyme as he call you thens vnto ſome other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. The which thynge yff ye are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to do, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do ye pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly followe your vocation, in gyvynge hym thankes for al thynges, havynge all wayes a ſure confi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dence that he wyll never leave you vnpro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vyded, &amp; that ye ſhall new wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a howffe to lodge in, ſeynge that for his ſake, you haue lefte that which was your owne. For he hathe ſo promyſed vs in his goſpel, ſayinge, I ſaye vnto you off a truthe, the re ys no man that dothe forſake his how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſſe, pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, brytherin,<note place="margin">Math. 19. Mar 10. Luc. 18.</note> wyffe or childrin for the kyngdom off God, that ſhall no. reſſayve myche more in this worlde, &amp; in the worlde to com, everlaſtyng lyffe. Are ye in doute, that Ieſus Chriſt wyll not performe vnto you this his promys? Dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te it not, for wheras you, do forgo but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb facs="tcp:12546:55"/>howſſe for his ſake, ye ſhall fynde a great many off howſſes off your fayght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brytherin open redy to reſſayve you. The lorde wyll prouide for you as he dyd for his prophete Elias fleyng from the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce off Achab,<note place="margin">9. Reg. 17</note> out off his contrye, a wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe off Gerepta, a frynde in a ſtrange lande that ſhall miniſter vnto your neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s: yea he wyll prouyde for you, as he dyd for his ſeruant Paul, a trew Aquila and a very Pryſcills, who wyll not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be redy to reſſayve you Ito theyre hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, but alſo inſtructe you in a more a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple knowlege off the truthe as they dyd Apol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lo. Wherfor my dere brytherin &amp; faight full fryndes I moſt hartely exhorte you, that durynge the tyme off your exile, and whylle it pleaſethe the lorde ye dwell in ſtrange contryes, as it were in places off progreſſe, that you do lyve ryghtouſlye, holely, and as it be comethe the chyldrin off God: to wyt, in al honeſtye, in trew humilite, in perfyte veryte, in an vnfay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned peace, in prompte obedience, inchari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te not fayned, in laborynge with your ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bes and in ſeruynge one a nother, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the habylyte that the lorde hath gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, &amp; in ſo doynge take no thought
<pb facs="tcp:12546:55"/>how you ſhall lyve in tyme to come, or wher with you ſhalbe fede and clothed, leve this damnable and vnprofytable care and thought takynge vnto the infydeles &amp; idolaters. God your father knoweth farre better then you, wheroff you haue nede, and he wyll gyve it you, in tyme &amp; place, doute you not: for he dothe noryſhe and preſerue the yerbes off the earthe, the byrdes off the eayre, &amp; the beaſtes off the felde, which all are no thynge in compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſon off you: Yea he dothe alſo norythe his aduerſaryes ffor whom the worlde was not made. Wherfor let it new enter into your thoughtes that he wyll forfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke you, but be off this moſt certaynly aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſured, that he wyll all wayes prouy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for you, all though you are not able to foreſe and conſyder the tyme, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor the meanes, how. For yff it pleaſe hym he wyll aſſiſte yonre neceſſite by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration off ſome off his creatures. Yff it pleaſe hym, he wyll helpe you, with out vſynge any off his creatures, as an in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ther vnto: for his almyghty pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er ys not anexed nor bounde vnto his cre, atures. And therfor my dere fryndes, the ſcriptures often tymes recordethe vn
<pb facs="tcp:12546:56"/>to vs, that the helpe off man ys all to gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther vayne as ſayeth the prophet Sauid,<note place="margin">pſal. 59.</note> that ys to ſaye it ys all to gyther vnprofy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table &amp; ſerueth to no vſe of it ſelfe, with out the lorde with ſaffe to blyſſe the ſame. And therfor the ſcriptures doth often ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes forbyd vs, not to put oure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in men, and namly in princes, who truly are but men.<note place="margin">pſal. 117.</note> That ys to ſaye, they are no thynge. For the holy goſt ſayeth playnly, that euery one that truſtethe in man,<note place="margin">Iere. 17.</note> ys accurſed. Wherfor we may not ſeke for helpe at men, for there ys none. We may not haue oure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, al thought they be kynges and prynces, and the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of kyngdoms and contryes: for yff we truſte in men, then do we no thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge els but leane vpon a broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reede,<note place="margin">Eze. 29.</note> which wyll make vs fall, &amp; in brekynge, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de oure hande and mayme vs: that ys to ſaye, it cannot be choſſen, but that ſome myſchyffe ſhall ther by happen vnto vs. for it lyethe not in men, no not in pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, any thynge to ſuccore your calamite, and all though they can, yet wyll they not. And al though they coulde, &amp; woul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de: yet may they not, for as myche as they haue vowed the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarye na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, neuerto
<pb facs="tcp:12546:56"/>helpe you, as longe as you ſeke the glorie off God in his goſpell: that ys to ſaye, tyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhuche tyme, as before them you denye your God, your profeſſion and fayght, to ſave therby your carnall lyffe. The which thynge in very dede, ys no helpe. but a rewyne: ys no commodyte, but a hyndrance: ys no pleaſure, but a payne. for what ſhould it profyte vs, my dere fryndes, to wyn all the worlde,<note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> &amp; then to loſe oure owne ſoulles? Laſt a ſyde, caſt aſyde then all confidence in man, ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver deſyre theyre helpe, ſeying that we can not vſe the ſame with out the preiudice of the glorye off oure lorde and God. That ys to ſaye, with out eternal damnation. With drawe your cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s from al cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures, come a waye, and depart with a ſure and perfyte fayght. Enter into the protection off the eternall God your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Beholde hym only, as it were, a parte and ſeperated from all creatures. Let it never enter into your thoughtes, that ye ſhoulde anexe and bynde, the infi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tye, wyſdom and power of your eternall God &amp; creator, vnto thynges cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ated. Couſyder that he was God with out begynynge, before he created &amp; made
<pb facs="tcp:12546:57"/>the worde, beynge only all myghty, all wyſſe, and all goodnes. And that by ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge off the worlde, he ys not become more myghtyer, wyſer, or better then he was before. Conſyder then, that all though all the creatures off the worlde dyd faylle you, at your nede, yet god re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth yours, who wyll all wayes helpe you, and that as well without the helpe off any creature, as with the ay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de off all his creatures to gyther. Be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red off that. And let oure truſt be no leſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe in God alone, then yff he were accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed with all thoſſe thynges that he hath created. This ys the trew Arche and pyller of a chriſtean fayght, and the-ſame taken a waye, fayght muſt nedes quayll. Wherfor my dere fryndes put in practyſſe this fayghtfull conſyderation and I enſure you that you ſhal fynde ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in ſhuche a conſolation as hyther to ye ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver taſted, and your affayres ſhall proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per better, then yff ye heaped all the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res off the worlde to gyther for the ſame. The lorde God, by Ieſus Chriſt his ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, comonicate vnto you all, his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rete, that in theſſe abyſmes off wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and palpable darcknes, which now
<pb facs="tcp:12546:57"/>ys happyned amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt you, he may ſo co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ducte you, that by a ſtronge fayght, &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hope ye may abyde in God, and in the profeſſion of his holy worde vnto thende. Wyſhyng no thyng ſo myche as the acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſhyng off the wyll off god, al thought it be with the preiudice of the wholl worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="Scriptural_citations">
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1</hi> Timoth. <hi>2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶ It ys a true ſayinge: yf we be dead with Chriſte, we ſhall alſo lyde with hym. Yff we be paciente, we ſhall alſo raigne with hym. If we denye hym, he alſo ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye vs. Iff we beleee not, yet abydethe he fayghtful. For he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not deuye hym ſelfe</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hebr. <hi>12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶ Stretche forth therefore agayne the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des that were let downe, &amp; the weake kne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es &amp; ſe that ye haue ſtrayght ſteppes vnto youre fete, leſt any haltynge turne ye one of the waye.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hebr. <hi>13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶ Remember the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are in bondes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thoughe ye were hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Be myndful of them that are in adverſitye. As ye whiche are yet in youre bodyes. Be not caryed a bout with divers &amp; ſtran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nynge. Anno. <hi>1556.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
